He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall, and
he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless
and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits, 1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels.
and saints. In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism,
to see and to know reality as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like? How do we engage
with it well? How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence? Orthodox Christian priests,
Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen De Young, post this live Colin show focused on
Enchantment in creation the union of the scene
and unseen as made by God and experienced by mankind throughout history. Welcome to the Lord of
Spirits. Thanks, voices, Steve. Greetings to you, Dragon Slater's giant killers and captains of
Capricorn and Niquity imputation. You're listening to the one hundred thirty second episode of the
Lord of Spirits podcast. Nevertheless, I am Father-Enter-Steven Daymak and with me is the scourge of
of YouTube live streams, Father Stephen D. Young, and we're live.
The great
gatekeeper, Mike shaved Arang and 10 again. We'll be taking your calls tonight beginning in the second half.
Before we go any further couple, couple quick notes I have to make. Okay. Thank you.
First, once again, people will probably notice we're coming to you. There are new earlier start time
so that old man, David, can get his beauty sleep. That's right. That's right.
And then, secondly, I do have to comment
of the audio that it beats.
and I have no issues with the content.
Yeah.
Content great.
Clearly from some one sermon podcast.
However, uh,
This was sounded like it was recorded on one of those two potato clocks
that we made with your high science class.
I think father that that was the voice of a very young father Thomas
Hopko.
Is that what it was?
So this is just a pretty sure.
You should.
Yeah, yeah, it's from a long time ago.
So so we were given a lot of time.
It's from a long time ago.
So we were given
And then, Interfaith was given boxes of tape recordings of talks and sermons and so forth
that were given by his family.
And we've been gradually digitizing them and making them into a podcast.
Okay.
Pretty sure this was like a phonograph record that was being played.
It's something like that.
It's actually old cassette tapes on some of the kids.
That explains.
And remember those, I can understand, but I was on the way to my actual grievance, which I'm
now airing.
that.
You people refused to air the earlier episodes of the whole Council of God Bible study because of my potato quality audio.
And now I see how I rate.
Yes, you rate below the legendary father Thomas Hopko.
I'm a but I think now that you've explained to me the age of it and the means of its provenance.
I think now I understand what needs to happen is
I need to die before I finish the second round.
I mean, and then you will use the potato quality audio to fill in the gaps.
Is that how this will work?
Because what some people may not know is that the earliest recordings of the whole Council
of God are so scratchy that they did not become part of your podcast and begins with the gospel
of Luke.
Even though you begin with Genesis, you've been in the first time around.
Yes, sir.
the princely sum of $21.87 to buy that audio recorder at Walmart.
And position it somewhere near me as I paste back and forth.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
I can I can picture in my mind because I know you recorded most of those in the coffee hour room
or maybe the room adjacent there at St. George and Charles and West Virginia. So I can always
imagine you doing that, you know, the refrigerator kicks on in the kitchen.
I can try to be a hoe, yeah.
And all that greats.
stuff. And I and I the real Mark of professionalism was that I had a whiteboard that I would write
and draw things on and point at and refer to on audio. Right. That was the real Mark of professionalism.
That's right. Before there was a YouTube kids. Yeah. This is back in the day. That's right.
Well, okay, that grievance has been lodged.
We will take it under advised.
this episode though, I don't know, it's likely I think that some people are going to get kind of excited at it.
Not because of the results.
It's not about giants, it's not about giants.
It doesn't necessarily mean it's going to be a good episode.
But we are, tonight we're going to be waiting into what is the relationship between the sacrificial system of the Torah,
The work of Christ and the gospel, what happens if you sin ex...
accidentally or on purpose. What is the relationship of all of that together because or accidentally on purpose?
Yeah, or on purpose accidentally. Because there is a whole lot of confusion out there, maybe among some of you,
about exactly what all of this means. And often, frankly, a lot of lines from the Old Testament are used as proof texts
ripped out of their context.
and thrown around to give this very kind of distorted theology.
So yeah, this is kind of a deep munker episode in some ways.
Yeah.
But we're also going somewhere.
Indeed.
Positive purpose.
Positive purpose. Yes. Yes.
So, where should we begin?
We're starting out here with specifically
out of the sacrificial system, right, in the Old Testament.
the old test, right?
We've done episodes, right?
We had a whole series of episodes of the sacrificial system.
But we're focusing, first here on sin offerings,
what they did and how they work, because there
are some very popular misconceptions out there
that are leading to the confusion.
This is especially amongst our evangelical friends,
Oh.
Although, like the rest of Protestantism in the US, frankly, a lot of it has become sort
of evangelicalized.
And there are a lot of Orthodox Christians who came from an evangelical background or
who grew up in an evangelical environment.
And so have taken on some of these ideas.
And even our Roman Catholic friends, just by virtue of being in the United States, culturally
and stuff have absorbed some of it.
these ideas, even though, for example, with them, it's not with their church
teachers, per se. Right? And it's not with the Orthodox church
teachers per se, but people have have these ideas in their head. They're
fixed and unshakable, which technically makes them delusions, psychologically
speaking, but we won't press that any further. But these are
Essentially.
what we're going to lay out here, especially in this first half, is these are modes of
Issa Jesus, of reading into the biblical text that have been taught or otherwise ingrained
into people.
Yeah, so that when you read or hear the text red, you just assume...
them. And so a lot of what we're going to start out doing is, okay, let's actually focus
it. Is that actually there in the text? So we're going to start out by, and this is going
to be a somewhat lengthy and repetitive reading. But if you're not into lengthy and repetitive,
What are you doing listening to this show?
Um, we're not that repetitive.
Oh, I say the same.
stuff over and over again. I sometimes try to get you to do like retro episodes. Hey,
let's go revisit that. You're like, oh, I got some of those. Well, yeah, I mean, if I wanted
to just give the same lecture over and over again, I'd be, you know, teaching somewhere.
I mean, the other you looped your other podcast, although it took you what 10 years, 12 and
Yeah, yeah.
So no promises on this one, everybody.
Yeah.
another co-host and we'll go back and just redo each episode in the exact same order.
Um finally move on with my life. Yeah or maybe they should replace both of us. Maybe
it will be like the man show after like, the review will let Adam Corolla. The new Lord of
spirits podcast will basically be a drink review show. They'll bring in like yeah they'll
So bringing like Joe Rogan and Bill Burr or something and like prop them up.
Anyway.
But we're going to read a link that we're going to read pretty much the whole thing of chapter four of the book of Leviticus, which probably isn't your favorite book, but maybe it should be at least higher up on the list than it is.
Yeah.
So this is where sin offerings, what therefore and how they're done is laid out.
So Father Andrew is going to read that. We're having him do this early in the episode because he's going to start to, you know.
not off a little toward the end.
I'm already young and
yeah and that's just me boring you.
And then we're going to take a look at some of the things that are commonly read into this text
and ask if reading them in even works, even makes sense.
Little low on whether it's justified but is it even reasonable to try to read them in?
That's where we're going here.
So
Pay attention here.
During it while Father Andrew goes through this and we will then work through it.
Do some commentary.
All right everybody, pull out your Bibles.
Turn to chapter four of Leviticus.
Let's or drill.
That's right.
Oh, I love sword drills.
Leviticus chapter four.
And the Lord spoke to Moses saying,
speak to the people of Israel saying if anyone's
sins unintentionally, in any of the Lord's commandments about things not to be done, and
does any one of them. If it is the anointed priest who sins, thus bringing guilt on the
people, then he shall offer for the sin that he is committed a bull from the herd without
blemish to the Lord for a sin offering. He shall bring the bull to the entrance of the
tent of meeting before the Lord and lay his hand on the head of the bull and kill the
bull before the Lord. And the anointed priest shall take some of the blood of the bull and
and bring it into the tent of meeting.
the priest shall dip his finger in the blood, and sprinkle part of the blood seven times
before the Lord in front of the veil of the sanctuary, and the priest shall put some
of the blood on the horns of the altar of fragrant incense before the Lord that is in
the tent of meeting, and all the rest of the blood of the bull he shall pour out at the base
of the altar of burnt offering that is at the entrance of the tent of meeting.
And all the fat of the bull of the sin offering he shall remove from it, the fat that covers
the entrails and all the fat that is on the entrails and the two kidneys
with the fat that is on them at the loins and the long lobe of the liver that he should
remove with the kidneys just as these are taken from the ox of the sacrifice of the peace
offerings and the priests shall burn them on the altar of burnt offering.
But the skin of the bull and all its flesh with its head, its legs, its entrails and its
dung, all the rest of the bull he shall carry outside the camp to a clean place to the ash
heap and so burn it up on a fire of wood on the ash heap that shall be burned up.
the whole congregation of Israel sins unintentionally.
and the thing is hidden from the eyes of the assembly, and they do any one of the things that by the Lord's commandments ought not to be done, and they realize their guilt, when the sin which they have committed becomes known, the assembly shall offer a bowl from the herd for a sin offering, and bring it in front of the tent of meeting.
And the elders of the congregation shall lay their hands on the head of the bowl before the Lord, and the bowl should be killed before the Lord.
Then the anointed priest will bring some of the blood of the ball into the tent of meeting
and the priest will dip his finger in the blood and sprinkle its seven t-
times before the Lord in front of the veil.
And he shall put some of the blood on the horns of the altar that is in the tent of meeting
before the Lord, and the rest of the blood, he shall pour out at the base of the altar
burnt offering that is at the entrance of the tent of meeting, and all its fat, he shall
take from it and burn on the altar.
Thus shall he do with the bull, as he did with the bull of the sin offering, so shall he do
with this.
And the priests shall make a tonement for them, and they shall be forgiven.
And he shall carry the bull outside the camp and burn it up as he burned to the first
bull.
the sin offering for the
the assembly. When a leader sins, doing unintentionally any one of the things that by the commandments
of the Lord, his God ought not to be done and realizes his guilt, or the sin which
he has committed is made known by him, he shall bring as his offering a goat, a male
without blemish, and shall lay his hand on the head of the goat and kill it in the place
where they kill the burnt offering before the Lord. It is a sin offering. Then the priest
shall take some of the blood of the sin offering with his finger and put it on the horns of
the altar burnt offering and pour out the rest of its blood at the base of the
of burnt offering. In all its fat, he shall burn on the altar like the fat of the sacrifice of
peace offerings, so the priests shall make a tonement for him for his sin, and he shall be forgiven.
If any one of the common people sins unintentionally in doing any one of the things that by the
Lord's commandments ought not to be done and realizes his guilt, or the sin which he has committed is
made known to him, he shall bring for his offering a goat, a female without blemish for his sin which he
has committed.
And he shall lay his hand on the head of the sin offering and kill the sin offering in the
place of burnt offering, and the priest will take some of its blood with his finger and
put it on the horns of the altar of burnt offering and pour out all the rest of its blood
at the base of the altar.
In all its fat, he shall remove as the fad is removed from the peace offerings, and the priest
shall burn it on the altar for pleasing aroma to the Lord, and the priest shall make a
tonement for him, and he shall be forgiven.
We're almost there, everybody.
If he brings a lamb as his offering for a sin offering, he shall bring a female without
blemish and lay his hand on the head of the synophring and
kill it for a sin offering in the place where they kill the burnt offering. Then the priest shall take
some of the blood of the sin offering with his finger and put it on the horns of the altar of
burnt offering and pour out all the rest of its blood at the base of the altar. And all its fat
he shall remove as the fat of the lamb is removed from the sacrifice of peace offerings
and the priest so burn it on the altar on top of the Lord's food offerings. And the priest shall make
a tonement for him for the sin which he has committed and he shall be forgiven.
Okay, pop quit. No, I'm not to the
same. That was a pregnant pause there,
father. See, you're going to sleep.
Well, I mean, you were lulling me off to I
know, I know, it's my so horrific
tones. It was hypnotic. It was
the repetition of certain words.
So yeah, so that's that.
I mean, it seems pretty straightforward, right?
We basically got slight variations on theme four times in a row.
The main difference being different animals, right, based on the different people involved,
who were offering the sin offering.
So we're going to look at a few, like we said, a few of the assumptions that get kind of
red into the text, right?
the first.
one of these is one that comes up once in a while because I have many times said on this
show and other places and two parishioners and probably in my sleep to my wife that there's
not a place in the Old Testament where sins are placed on an animal and then it is sacrificed.
Hmm. Right. And every once in a while, when I do that,
not with my wife when I say it in my sleep,
but in other circumstances,
someone who has been taught to read the text this way
will point me to a passage like Leviticus 4
that we just read and say, well, look,
before they kill the animal,
whether it's a goat or a lamb or what have you,
they lay their hand on it.
They kill it, see?
And so what it says, they lay their hands on it and they kill it, that's where they're
putting the sins on the animal.
Yeah, and you kill the animal with the sins on it so that you don't have to be killed.
Right.
You punish the animal for the sins involved, right?
And there's this whole substitutionary thing going on, right?
Thanks, Alan.
You get to that part in a second, right?
So they say that's what's going on in...
sin offering. It just doesn't spell it out. Right? Because obviously it doesn't literally
say there anything about putting sins on the animal. Right? And maybe they will take you
to, or maybe they'll just refer generally to the fact that in Leviticus 16, now keep
in mind, if you've been paying attention, Leviticus 16 would be 12 chapters after Leviticus
yep
The David Tellment ritual, there's our two goat friends again, where with the goat for
a zazel, the scapegoat, they lay hands upon it and Aaron pronounces the sins of the people
over it when he lays his hands on it. And they say, so see.
It doesn't spell it out in any of these other places.
It only actually says that here in this one place,
the Leviticus XVI with the name of Atonement.
But you're supposed to infer that all the other places,
where it says to lay heads on the animal before it's killed,
you're also supposed to put the sins on it there as well.
Okay.
Now there's some obvious problems right off the bat.
Like how when you're reading...
is for would you infer something from 12 chapters later?
Yeah, and in Leviticus 16, it doesn't say this applies everywhere and always nor like
like in this.
This is the usual process.
Yeah, exactly.
In this chapter, we even get and then you do this like you do this other thing.
You do this like you do this other thing.
Yeah.
You know, but but that's not.
If you're going to say it once, if you're going to say it once, and then expect it to be
be inferred in the other place.
You'd think the one place where you said it would be the first place.
Yeah.
And then you infertile later places.
Now even that would be pushing it because as you just heard Leviticus for it's not shy about repeating instructions.
Right in the exact same words.
Yep.
It doesn't leave you to infer anything
It gives you the whole set of instructions of instructions repetitiously over and over again in each case.
with each animal. So that's also a problem, right? There's also the problem of the animal
where the sins are pronounced during the laying out of hands. The scapegoat, of course, is
not then killed. It's right. It is let away. It is not killed. It is nor is it sacrificed.
right? Okay so you're supposed to infer that this animal that isn't killed and isn't
that you follow the same procedure from that on all the animals that are killed and our sacrifice,
even though the text doesn't say so. Right?
You, you hopefully anyone who formerly held that theory has already given it up, but just in case.
Let's really narrow it on this.
And let's just stick with Leviticus 16. Let's not talk about it further into any other passage.
Let's talk about Leviticus 16 itself.
Just the
day of atonement ritual. Yeah. Because hands are laid on the goat for a
zeal, the scapegoat, and the sins are pronounced over it. And
it's sent into the wilderness. The other goat, the goat for Yahweh, is
offered as a sin offering. It's not the one that has the sins spoken
Yes, it has hands laid on it.
So, are we to infer?
that when it says that the Gofri always offered is a sin offering, that the sins were also
read over it even though Leviticus 16 doesn't say so.
So that the same sins were pronounced over both goats according to this theory.
That the text doesn't, Leviticus 16 doesn't say that doesn't say you do that with both
of goats. It says you do that with the goat that's not a sin offering. Does it?
You do it with both.
Yep.
But even beyond it, not saying that, right,
it clearly being Isaac Jesus,
you're just adding something to the text of scripture.
Why would you do it on the two goats?
Yeah, are they already doing like daily sin offerings?
Yeah, well, first why would you do it to both goats?
Right?
If I put the sins on the goat for Yahweh
and I kill it,
And offering is a sin offering. Why do I need to put those same sins on a second goat?
Yeah. What's the point of that?
And then as you just pointed out, if we're already doing this sin offering procedure with those sins
in the daily sin offerings, why am I doing the day of Atomit ritual at all?
Yeah. Yeah.
to have it all those things would take a care of.
So you've already probably got it into your head, right? That that dog don't hunt in terms
of trying to read in, right? The the pronouncing of sins over every sin offering. But just in
case, there's still some doubt in your head. I mean, this may be a stop beating him
father Steven he's already
dead, but I don't care. I am pounding this thing to powder tonight. We have numbers eight.
Numbers again, another book of the Bible that's everyone's favorite, but should be higher on your list.
Numbers eight verses five through 13. Okay, starting with verse five. And the Lord spoke to Moses saying,
take the Levites from among the people of Israel and cleanse them. Thus you shall do to them to cleanse them,
Sprinkle the water of purification.
upon them, and lets them go with a razor all over their body, and wash their clothes and
cleanse themselves, then let them take a bowl from the herd and its grain offering a
fine flower mixed with oil, and you shall take another bowl from the herd for a sin offering.
And you shall bring the Levites before the tent of meeting and assemble the whole congregation
of the people of Israel.
When you bring the Levites before the Lord, the people of Israel shall lay their hands on
the Levites. And Aaron shall offer the Levites before the Lord.
as a wave offering from the people of Israel that they may do the service of the Lord.
Then the Levites shall lay their hands on the heads of the bulls and you shall offer
the one for a sin offering and the other for a burnt offering to the Lord to make a tonement
for the Levites.
And you shall set the Levites before Aaron and his sons and shall offer them as a wave
offering to the Lord.
So in this passage.
we read about how the Levites as a tribe are being offered by the other Israelite tribes
as a sacrifice to the Lord. So they lay hands upon them. The designate them as a sacrifice.
And then of course as we just heard, they pronounced the sins of the people upon them and
beat the Levites to death. No. Not what we just did. Right. But wait. And if you're going
say to me, well, no, you don't read it in there where they're laying hands on the
Levites. My question to you is why not? Yeah. How do you know which Torah
passages to read that into and which one's not to read it into? Right? If we're
going to just read things in that aren't there, shouldn't we read it into all the
place? And this isn't just, well, no, this is laying on hands like
No, it's not. We picked this example.
on purpose. Yeah. Right. So the
Levites are being offered as a
sacrifice. Wave offering. Yes.
Now, yes, they're not literally
offered as a wave offering. Okay.
The other Israelites did not like
hoist the Levites up in the air and
wave them back and forth.
Or make the Levites do the wave or
something, right? That's not. Right.
She went first. But this is right.
They'll lay hands on them in a sacrificial content.
So if laying hands on something in a sacrificial context means
pronouncing the sins over them imputing your sins to them then why doesn't it mean that here?
If that's what it means
Because it clearly doesn't mean that here, right?
Which means
I'm sorry, but you've got no case
Those of you who want to argue that you should just read the scapegoat procedure.
to sin offerings. You have no biblical case. Yep, this is a, a, you know, I can be nice about
it and say, this is just some confusion. I can be less nice about it and say, this is a
tradition of men, right? Which you have rejected the scriptures for. But you know, and weapons
against, but that's that's what it is right it's not there it's not the
It's not how it works.
So that's one.
This idea that somehow sins were imputed to the animal.
Before it was before it was killed and that is a primary element in the sin offering.
So that didn't happen.
Okay, that didn't happen.
Second assumption is related.
Right.
So this assumption is all should already be falling apart in your head.
right based on that previous one falling apart.
But this one has to do with the idea that there is some kind of substitution going on in
the sacrificial system, so kind of substitution.
Now I have, this is for our orthodox brothers and sisters in Christ.
You need to stop saying this whole we believe in substitutionary.
just not penal substitution thing. That's nonsense. That doesn't mean anything. We'll have a little more on that later. Okay. But the idea here is that the person bringing the offering, the sin offering, by virtue of their sin should receive the death penalty.
Yeah, every but instead the goat lamb. Yeah, the goat lamb ram sheep. Right. That's bull calf. Whatever.
That gets killed. So sure that death that is out. I mean, people will probably point to
Roman 623. The wages of sin is death. I mean, I remember, you know, growing up in an evangelical
context I was told if you sin even one time you deserve
to die. You know, that's the way it is. It doesn't matter. No matter how small it is. You
tell one lie to your mom and dad. Yes. Well, I could do all three through a verse,
taken out of context. So, yeah. If you actually read what St. Paul is doing there in Romans,
he's contrasting the wages of sin is death, but the gift of God is eternal life.
Yeah, right.
Jesus Christ.
He's contrast.
Wages versus gift. That's the point of contrast.
He's not trying to argue anything about whether every sin is worthy of death.
Right because
What you find out if you read the Torah, we're talking about the Torah here. We're talking about Leviticus, right?
Read the Torah
Not every sin has the death penalty in the Torah. No
No
In fact, as we'll see when we get into the thorough, you will sometimes get pushback
for people when you suggest to them that the sacrificial system could deal with death
penalty cases and people could not be executed.
Yeah.
Well, and also frankly, they've done another presupposition.
In first John chapter five, it says it's not all sin is on to death.
Yes.
I mean, it's just explicitly there.
because St. John has read the Torah. But, right, so, but you can see how that's
across purposes too, right? Like, oh no, if that's in requires your death, you can't
go and sacrifice animals to forgive it. But then the same person turns around and
says, oh, the way sacrifices work is that the animal dies instead of you. Yeah, no.
like. So, this
This is why we're calling it confusion.
We're calling it confusion because the same person will make directly contradictory statements
like that.
Right.
So this presuppose that there's death penalty for all sins.
But only is there like not obviously the death penalty for all sins.
There are different, you can call them punishments, you can call them means of reconciliation
a restoration, different penances, whatever language you want to use.
Not every sin, right, and you know petty theft was not putish by death under the Torah.
Right.
If you want an example, here's an example from Exodus chapter 22 verses 1 through 4.
Okay.
If a man steals an ox or a sheep and kills it or sells it, he shall repay five oxen for
And 4-4-4-4-4-4-4-4-4-4-4-4-4-4-4-4.
a sheep. If a thief is found breaking in and is struck so that he dies, there shall be no blood
guilt for him. But if the sun has risen on him, there shall be blood guilt for him. He shows
surely pay. If he has nothing, then he shall be sold for his theft. If the stolen beast is found
alive in his possession, whether it is an ox or a donkey or a sheep, he shall pay double.
Okay, so we have actually two examples.
They're sort of.
nested within each other. So we'll start with the you steal something. Right? Notice if you steal
something and you kill it or sell it, you are not killed in response. Right? So the sin offering you go
an offer for the sin of stealing.
It does not make sense for that to be like, oh, well, I need to be killed for stealing. Well, no you don't
But the animals gonna die instead. Well wait, no
Right. No, you're gonna make restitution
That's if you if you kill the animal or sell it if you still have the animal then you just pay back to you pay it less
You have to hook a little hook hook a little bit because you could return the original thing you stole
plus of extra, right?
But again,
You're not liable to death.
You'll get stoned to death for that.
Right? So
doesn't make sense.
You notice even the case of killing a person a thief breaks into your house
You end up struggling with a bit killing him. That's punished differently based on whether it's day or night
Hmm
So manslaughter isn't even punished with death in some cases. Yeah
So how does it make, how does this substitution?
death thing with all sin offerings work when there is no death required for most sins in the Torah.
Right? Now, on top of this, let's suppose in imagination land that this assumption
were correct, that this thing being read in was correct. And so, okay, person has committed
the scene.
say theft. There is a price to be paid and that price is the thief's life. Let's just
assume that. Even though that's not what the Torah says. But we'll assume that. So the
animal is killed instead of him. The animal is substituted for him. It is killed in his
place. It dies the death that is rightfully his. So he is now forgiven. Does he still have
to pay back the person he stole from.
Yes, it's he does.
Right. Well, why if that's how the sacrifice works? Right. Exactly. Does it pay all the penalty?
For sins. I thought the animal paid the penalty. Yeah, which was death.
Yep. Right. Or
He goes and he returns the ox plus an extra one because the ox is still alive. And then he says, I don't have to worry about that whole
sin offering thing because I took care of it.
That's that's not how this works.
Yeah, right?
It does it again.
It doesn't make any sense.
Okay.
And once again, as we pointed out before on the show,
I know the killing of the animal isn't even ritualized.
The killing of the animal is not the sacrifice part.
We don't have any instructions on how to kill it.
but to kill it, but even more importantly.
Right either either rewind this or go look at Leviticus 4 again
Who kills the animal
Who lays their hand on the animal and who kills it?
It's the priest
No, oh actually no no, it's whoever's doing the offering. It's whoever's bringing the offering
Then the priest takes it and sacrifices it. Yeah, that's right
Yeah, because I remember that at the first time it is the priest but he's the one
who's the center and it's offering it for himself. Yes. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Right?
Noted that towards the end. It was not the. Yeah. It was doing the killing.
Meeting the killing of the animal is not a priestly action.
Hmm. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. It is not the sacrifice part.
The sacrifice part is what the priest does with it after.
So he does with it after. Yeah. We need to get away from this idea that sacrifice
is that the
word sacrifice mean. And within this context, I understand English, you know, but within
the context of the scriptures, sacrifice does not mean killing a thing. Yes. Yes. This
really changes. We've got too much other material. So we're not going down this rabbit trail.
Don't worry, Father Andrew. But it really changes how you read Hebrews. Once you understand
Christ as the High Priest offering himself as a sacrifice.
is not primarily about his death,
about what he does after his death.
And it's not like some kind of weird suicide.
Yeah, right?
But it's not his death itself.
You've been taught that it's Christ's death itself
that is the sacrifice.
That's not what Hebrew says.
You know, Hebrew says Christ is the high priest
that is the heavenly sanctuary,
and offers a sacrifice.
You do that after
The sacrifice is dead. Yeah, yeah, and just as a
As a shout out we've given many many times now, but very worth making again
You know father Jeremy Davis's book welcoming gifts is really thoroughly explores exactly what is sacrifice
And all of that so we don't need to do the rabbit trail. It has been written as a book
Yes
For us and just one of the books that father Stephen has said I'm glad someone wrote it now. I don't have to go
Yeah.
go and go reread Hebrews while you're at it with that in mind and see what you understand.
So once again, what do we see? Best case scenario, this whole substitution thing is confusion,
worst case scenario, this is a tradition of men that is putting it not the words of scripture.
By the way, I would be remiss if I did not.
had, you know, being a good ancient faith ministry's employee that welcoming gifts is now
a podcast as well. And they just released a second episode. So so there you go. Everyone
go to is it like you see like ex well, maybe I shouldn't do this. I don't know. Is he basically
going through the book is he expanding on the book? Is he? It's related to the book. Yeah,
it's related to the book. It's a lot of it is about application and, you know, all that
kind of stuff. Okay, so there's new material.
in the podcast. Absolutely. Absolutely. The book is the jumping off point for the podcast.
Yep. Yep. So the yeah, it's called welcoming gifts has the same name. But but yeah. Yeah.
Okay. So yeah, see I'm helping you here. I'm helping you. Thank you. Thank you.
Even if you've read the book, right, there's there's there's more there. There's more
where that came from in this pocket.
Indeed.
Right, so,
Tradition number three.
Right. Man made tradition number three. I said, piece of ice of Jesus number three. Third
thing that gets assumed and read into this text is, now this isn't the other two have
been sort of adding words and concepts. This one is a little more understandable because
this is based on how you interpret or understand a word that is actually there. Yeah. Yeah.
Okay. So this is a, this is more of a misinterpretation than
pure isegesus. Yeah, there's the word unintentional, at least is the word that was in the translation
that I read earlier. Right.
Unintentionally. Someone says unintentionally. Other translations will have involuntarily
or refer to involuntary sins. That kind of idea. Right.
And so people get this idea that all of these sacrifices that we read.
from liverticus chapter four earlier were for sins that people committed without meaning
to or without like they did it on purpose. Yeah, accidentally. And but the thing is, the
thing is a number of the sins that are the kind of thing you would offer these sacrifices
for. There is no way to do them accidentally. Like I accidentally did an adultery. Yeah,
whoops, you know, no, that's not
I didn't even realize till three weeks later, so what pointed it out to me or I accidentally stole his goat
Yeah, you know I
Guess there are scenarios in which you could say oh, I took the wrong goat, but that's not how it works in the ancient world
That means you went to someone else's property and took their goat you had been coveting your neighbor's goat. That's right
Yeah, these are not these are not accidental involuntary and that's
That's not what's going on here
We'll talk about what that means, but so that's the assault
You will hear this a lot.
This one has been making the rounds a lot very publicly.
I know it's weird.
I was never really...
That's why we're hammering on this one right now.
But it's not, it's totally a thing on the interwebs.
Yeah.
I think, you know, I think part of what's happening is,
for whatever reason, now a lot of these sacrifices and stuff are becoming interesting
to people in some evangelical traditions again.
So they're looking at this stuff and they're trying to read it in a way
reading in a way that that
And that supports the theology that they have about what sacrifices for and all that
goes to.
Yeah.
But so what this would mean if that's a correct interpretation.
If we were talking about here are accidental sins, right?
Truly unintentional, right?
That would mean that the entire sacrificial system, everything outlined.
in Exodus, Leviticus and Numbers,
in terms of the sacrificial system,
in terms of the sacrifices of the great feasts,
whether we're talking about the 70 bulls
for the 70 nations, whether we're talking
about the Day of Atonement, all of this,
all of that is just for dealing with whoopsies.
Yeah.
All of this is for dealing with accidents.
And there is no system in place for dealing with any sin
that anyone commits...
deliberately. Right? Nothing. There's no no way to do it. So I guess the person who stole
had to restore the stuff but there's no sacrifice involved at all. But wait, we literally just
read how that was required. Right. So, right? That doesn't make any sense. Bluntly. We
the super elaborate system for dealing with whoopsies, but you know, your mom asks you
if you ate the cupcake and you say no, oh, there's no way we'd deal with it. That's
it. That's it. You're going to get Hannah. There is no, no way to deal with this. I mean,
it's why they have to have all those kids because they have to execute them lifting
right? Yes. No, no reconciliation possible. Right? Cut off from among the people. Uh,
This doesn't make sense.
This doesn't.
that's clearly not what's going on in the Torah.
Okay?
This also asks us to believe that, again,
despite what the Torah says repeatedly,
that there was the death penalty for accidents.
Yeah.
Especially if you believe to the previous two,
presuppositions that we just showed don't work,
but if you do hold to those, right?
That you're saying that you deserve death
for all the-
things that you did completely unintentionally. Right? This is absurd. Right? This is absurd.
You're clearing your ground, right? You accidentally knocked up a rock and hit someone in the eye. You
must die. Right? This like have you read the Bible? Like is anything like that even in the tenor of the
Bible.
anything that had anything to do with the character of God, right? Like the God of the Bible at
least, right? No, right? That doesn't make any sense. And then what even is the concept of
culpability? And there is a concept of culpability in the Bible. We just proved her over that Exodus
passage we read, where there's a different penalty for killing an intruder if it was at night versus
in the day.
That's...
assessment of culpability.
Yeah, that's what it was at night.
It was in the dark.
You didn't know what was happening.
You didn't intend to kill the person.
It was unintentional.
Therefore, you are not guilty of his blood.
You are not a murderer.
Whereas if you do it in broad daylight
and know what you're doing and you kill him,
you are a murderer.
That's culpability.
That's assessing culpability based on circumstances.
Yeah.
Right?
And so if you say that,
This is only deals with accidental-
things and you deserve death for accident. I don't think right then the whole assessment
of culpability makes no sense right. If you took a goat thinking it was your goat and
then you found out, Oh, it's not my goat. And you go and bring it back to the person
who's going. It is you're not a thief making restitution. You're correcting an error. An
an error that you may not because you're sinful and wicked, but because you're human and
finite.
Yeah. Right? There's a difference between an error and a sin. Right? When I misremember
something on this podcast while we're live, so when that calls it, it asks me a question,
and I misremember a date or a name or something. Right? I don't go to confession for that
guys. You should. Right? If I deliberately lied to someone, I would need to...
go to confession. Right? But making a mistake, an honest mistake is exactly that, an honest
mistake. Right? That's not right. So you have to get rid of the whole idea of culpability,
which is found in the text of the Torah in order to make this presupposition about the
So the supply says we said that there is no
No forgiveness of voluntary sins.
And then someone, maybe I myself have done this.
Well, someone will say this kind of thing.
And I'll say, so what about King David?
Yeah, that was pretty deliberate.
You're right, he did like accidentally impregnate another man's wife
and then murder him to cover it up.
Yeah. Oops.
Yeah.
All right.
Like, I mean, the sequence is pretty clearly laid out.
Yes.
That's, um, yeah.
And yet he's forgiven and people will say to me it was was that well, that was it through
the sacrificial system for deliver it since God just chose to forgive them.
Okay.
Now.
Now we're officially back in crazy town.
Okay.
This
is one of those things where people are believing things that do not make sense together.
So apparently if you deliberately sin, you do something on purpose, something horrible
on purpose, something that is worthy of death and the Torah on purpose.
And you pray and you honestly can try it, you ask God for forgiveness, he can apparently
now just forgive you in the Old Testament.
Yeah, what is the deal with all those sacrifices?
But if you do something,
and-
Exadata, you've got to go and offer, you know,
impoverish yourself offering from your herds and flocks
to get forgiven for the boo-boo you made.
Right?
So God could just forgive sins by hand waving
for deliberate ones, even serious deliberate ones,
but he can't overlook-
Look unintentional ones.
Those we need this whole sacrificial system.
This doesn't make any sense, folks.
This doesn't make any sense.
Okay, the sacrificial system clearly
is for dealing with actual sins
committed by actual people
at a big part of it being an actual sin, right?
Is that you took some action you could have known
that you should not take.
I mean, yeah.
David definitely knew that Bathsheba was not-
not his wife. Yes. And then when she got pregnant, he tried to lie and conspire to as quickly
as possible get her husband to sleep with her so he could pass the child off as being
her husband's. Okay. So there's another level of sin. He didn't do that accidentally.
Right. And then with that plan didn't work because her husband was too righteous of a man
to go along with it. He has him killed.
Right.
There's nothing accidental there.
And God does not, you know, send a lightning bolt.
Yes.
That's okay.
Now, all that said about how none of this makes any sense.
This one, any more than the other two, as such as we talked about, none of this makes any
sense.
None of these dogs on.
Why are people lately, especially?
has become a really popular meme now to say.
The Old Testament, Sacrificial System did not, there's no way in the Old Testament to
be forgiven for deliberate sins, for things you did on purpose.
Why has that become a homie?
Well, what they're trying to do, right, if you, and I'm going to be fair, the people who
bring this up, bring it up into context, and the context they bring it up in is they're
wanting to make a contrast between the Old Testament sacrificial system and the sacrifice
of Christ.
Yeah, that's what they're trying to do and say
The sacrifice of Christ, this is so much better.
Yeah.
Because the Old Testament stuff, the Old Testament sacrifice couldn't, could only deal
with accidental unintentional sins, they say.
Right?
Whereas Christ sacrificed the forgiveness that comes in Christ, forgive me.
So there is a positive motivator here that's causing them to say this.
Even though what they're saying doesn't make sense when you really push on it, as we've
just seen.
Right?
This is what...
they're trying to do, they're trying to make this contrast, right? That now in the New Testament,
in the New Covenant with Christ's sacrifice, right? It's not just in Voltaire since,
you're forgiven for voluntary sins. And then though, they read Hebrews chapter 10 verse 26.
Yeah, which says, for if we go on sending deliberately after receiving the knowledge of the truth,
there no longer remains a sacrifice for sins. Uh oh.
It's not a good pregnant pause there, Father. That's our first half. All right. Well, on that
cliffhanger, we're going to take our first break and we'll be right back. Father Andrew
Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next
of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Poised between east and west,
between Orthodox and Catholic,
Lithuania, the last of Europe's pagan nations,
did not forget its ancient tales,
such as that of the giant
Tess Naringa, Egley Queen of Serpents, and the Iron Wolf.
Rather, they fulfilled and enriched them with legends like the Hill of Crosses and the
miracle-working icon of our Lady of the Gate of the Dawn.
In the Wolf and the Cross, Father Andrew Stephen Daymac and Deacon Seraphim Richard Rowland
take a very personal pilgrimage into a land where history and legend have met and fused,
Orthodox Christians have lived as a minor-
for nearly seven centuries. Their faith found it upon the blood of martyrs and the witness of
dozens of saints. To find this book and others like it, you can go to store.AncientFaith.com.
Again, that is store.AncientFaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen
even to young. If you have a question, call now.
8552372346. That's 855AF radio.
Hey, we're back everybody. And boy, I see the call board is just lighting right up and I'm sure
Gatekeeper Mike is is friends will be trying to type out. I know. I know that just there were no calls for the whole first half.
And then suddenly as soon as this break started finishing up boom, boom, boom, boom.
Yeah, they're all very pleased that they're just
calling to say diddo. I'm sure exactly. Exactly. Wow, that brings me back. So yeah, yeah.
Oh, wow, some people hung up. I guess they're mad at that way. You just said I'm not sure.
Oh, that is what I was going to say. I'm going to never mind. It's right. He was just going to say,
Oh, no, I'm not gonna bother with that.
So yeah, we'll take a couple calls.
So first of all, we will...
take. I'm sure I'm going to mispronounce this here, but a notch from Texas, although
it the your phone says you're in Chicago. So welcome, Lord of Spheres podcast.
Hello greetings, fathers. Greetings. I'm sure mispronouncing your name again, you've called before.
Yes, I have. And last time I called in was from from Madison, Wisconsin, and I'm calling from
text us now.
around. Are you on the lamb? On the lamb. I'm not sure I know what that means. On the runs.
Yeah, I've been from law enforcement. Oh, from law enforcement. Oh, fortunately, I'm not.
So, okay, good. All right. All right. So what's on your mind, Anash?
Yes.
Yeah, so the place where you guys left off with kind of the new testament.
Just in kind of conversations with friends and family,
I think Dave, I guess sometimes pushed back on me
for I think not as much with the atonement part,
but in the place where it's like,
oh, well, Christ has offered the sacrifice
and therefore none of the ritual is necessary.
And I think I just wanted to get your thoughts on that
as...
you know, like, yeah, that kind of component because, you know, it talks like in some 50 or some 51,
you know, it talks about the heart and you guys mentioned about kind of the fusion.
Oh, okay. Okay. We will definitely get you. You're tracking with us, man.
Yeah, I mean, no, you're right. This is absolutely a thing. I mean, I was raised evangelical and
this idea that what Christ did means that all of the stuff that like, for instance, that we just
red from the
and whatever, that that's all simply over now.
You know, that, that, and they'll even say stuff like Jesus came to end religion, you
know, which there's a big problem with, there's a lot of problems with that.
One of the big problems with that is this idea that all of that is bad.
Well, he's the one who gave those commandments to begin with.
So like he came to save us from the
system that he gave or something, you know, like it just, it doesn't make sense, right?
This idea of Jesus versus religion. I remember a number of years ago, there was this big
this spoken word video that went around by a guy and it was titled something like,
why I love Jesus but hate religion. And I remember, you remember that one father?
I remember that one and my favorite response to that was
It was kind of snarky, but it was like,
I'm gonna do a video called,
why I love broccoli but hate vegetables.
But it's this idea, this idea that ritual,
that sacrifice and so forth is some kind of man-made thing.
And then Jesus came to stop all of that.
But that's basically sort of Marceonite.
It makes out the God of the Old Testament
be a different God than Jesus.
or at least strongly implies that, right?
So yeah, I mean, there's so many problems with that idea.
I don't know, father, what did you want to have to add
to that other than groaning at my reference to that?
Well, I think it was 2012 when that was.
Boy, that was a while ago.
Some like that.
Yeah.
So the part of the problem, of course, is, right?
Right.
Ritual is what the
guy who's higher church than me does, right? At least ritual when it's the bad kind, right?
Because these family members, I bet if they're Christian, go to the same place on most Sunday
mornings at pretty much the same time and do a sequence of the same things, probably in mostly the
same sequence. That's a
That's a ritual.
Right? That's a ritual.
There's a whole bunch of
rituals in the Old Testament.
But this idea that Christ comes
and he puts it into ritual.
That's equivalent to me to saying,
yeah, Christ came so he don't have to worship God anymore.
That's so weird.
Right? You see what I'm saying?
like.
Of course, we still worship God.
The people saying this to you, still, I'm assuming as best they know how, as they think
is right, at least, are trying to worship God.
Right?
So, you know, then the question is, well, no, Christ coming and offering Himself is a
sacrifice, it's put it into certain particular forms of ritual, or particular forms of
to which I say, yes, I agree we don't sacrifice animals anymore.
Yeah. Right.
We now celebrate the Eucharist, which is a thank offering and participate in Christ once we're all sacrifice through the Eucharist.
We don't sacrifice animals anymore. We don't get two goats on the day of atonement,
at least at my church, feasted the exaltation of the cross, we don't get two goats and send one out into the bio.
Right.
Those particular forms we don't do, but we still worship God.
And the way we worship God is in continuity with the way that God has always told us to
worship Him.
It's in continuity.
It doesn't mean every single detail is identical, right?
But it's in continuity.
Christ does not just start a new religion.
Christ really just started a new religion.
Why do we even have the Old Testament in our Bible?
Why don't we just have the New Testament?
If all that's done.
Yep. Right. Really.
I mean, honestly, the general evangelical
and a lot of Protestants reading of the Old Testament,
it makes no sense to have it in the Bible.
Because the way they read it as,
this is a whole bunch of practices
that have been done away.
with by Christ. And this is a whole bunch of prophecies, shadowy prophecies of Christ.
And now we see the truth of Christ in the Gospels. So why have it in your Bible? What's the
point? Well, that's what Marcy said. Right? Well, I don't think your average evangelical
thinks there's an evil Old Testament God. No, no, but I mean the DBH isn't an evangelical
right?
You're like your real Marcy and I it's they're not even juggles right but just to church. Why is it in your Bible? Yeah?
Why even have it why even read from it?
Right
Yep
There's commandments in it
But you think most of those are done away with the ones you don't think are done away with are
Repeated in the New Testament. So just use the New Testament
Yep
And the fact that you wouldn't do that the fact that you know our president evangelical friends
still have enough of original christian
in their religion, right?
That they know, no, I would never
take the Old Testament out of my Bible.
Well, maybe that should change how you read it then.
Maybe that view that the Old Testament
is just as inspired and just as valid
and just as important in your Bible
as the New Testament.
Maybe that ought to change the way you
understand the continuity between the
testaments to stay factor.
Yep. Alrighty, well thank you very much for that calling us and I'm sure we'll hear from you again.
There was a series of uncontroversial statements by me.
That's why people tune in to get these spicy takes. Next,
next we have Georgia calling from Birmingham, Alabama. Georgia, welcome to Lord Spirit's podcast.
Thank you.
Thank you, others.
I am calling to represent the dozens.
of women listeners of Lord of Spirits.
Because there are dozens of us.
There are, there are more than dozens.
There are more than dozens, you know, when we did,
when we did the Lord of Spirits conferences,
it was just about 50, 50, actually.
So that's amazing.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
You mean, I'll be showing up in the YouTube comments,
although actually it looks like there's plenty
of women in the chat tonight.
Wow.
But if I were a woman on the internet
I don't know that if I would admit to being a woman on the internet either.
I remember back in the 90s that joke always was that all the women on the internet are actually not
yeah, which was on some level kind of true because you know it was a certain subset,
especially the early 90s, the early 90s, the internet was was not what it is now. I'll just say
that. It was quite a certain subset of people at universities largely. Well, I will say the early
days.
of World of Warcraft, like female players all played male characters, so that people
wouldn't know that they were women and harassed them. And all the female characters you saw
were like weird dudes.
I mean, yep, yep, all true. But anyway, feel secure. What is your question?
I'm not a word collar,
it's just Georgia who I met in Birmingham.
Yes, yes, all right.
Well,
All right, well, we're in the presence of greatness everybody. This is an ancient faith.
So my question was about Genesis 316, the part where God is
sort of telling tells the serpent what will happen to him and then before telling Adam
that the earth will be cursed because of his actions, he tells the woman that she will be,
She will have her pain greatly increased in childbearing.
And I've heard sort of more orthodox perspectives on how
Adams, these words to Adam are more reflecting the new
reality of how creation will not work for him but there will be a
struggle between him and creation and how this is not, if I
understand right, this is not necessarily just a punishment from
God but a explanation.
of this is what you've done and this is what the consequences are.
My question is, is that different for Eve?
What is going on here for women? Is this just a punishment or is this something to do with
the way the new body of, you know, garments of skin will work?
The new body that God is giving them the new shape and form that humanity will take after the fall.
Yeah. What do you think, Father?
So it is essentially the same dynamic.
And so the way at this is, right,
we've talked before on the show about how,
we talk about before the fall, right,
in the creation of man and woman,
they have this shared task that they accomplish together
of
filling the earth and some doing it, right?
Setting the world in the creation and order and filling it with life.
Each of them has one of those that they've sort of major in and the other one that they minor in,
right? So the man sort of majors in putting things in order but participates in bringing life
into the world, the woman sort of majors in bringing life into the world and miners in or
participates in the putting of the world into order and they cooperate and they do this together.
That's the ideal. And so within the curse text in texts in Genesis 3, we see that each of them
still has that purpose. Each of them is still created for that goal.
But for both of them, it is now going to be with struggle and difficulty and hardship to do it.
So the man is still going to take the elements of the earth and put them in order, right?
And grow crops, but now there's going to be thorns, thistles, the sweat of his brow.
This is going to be hard.
This is going to be difficult, right?
His work is going to be difficult and hard task.
And the woman is still going to bring life into the world, but now it's going to be difficult
and painful and a struggle.
then added at the end of him talking
talking to to E or soon to be Eve, right, then woman, but soon to be Eve. He also says
remember that the bit about her desire being for her husband and him ruling over her, right?
That's talking about the cooperation between them breaking down, right? You doing this together,
you working together is going to be its own struggle, right, between between the two of you.
So the world into which?
They are expelled when they're expelled from paradise is one in which they still have this purpose got does not take this purpose away
He is not cutting them loose and completely cutting them up, right?
But now it is going to be difficult and a struggle in all ways and
When the language there what it talks about woman struggling in childbirth is not just talking about giving birth to a child
Right that is sort of
The archetypal example is
example, as we've talked about in the show of how a woman brings life very literally new
human life into the world in a very literal sense, right?
But that is an image for all of woman's purpose in bringing life into the world.
But it's also an image of, um, an image of all of being a mother, right?
Being a mother.
her first son is gonna
murder her second son.
Right.
Part of what happens in this world is not just that, yeah, it
hurts a lot while the baby is being born.
And then fortunately, biologically, through hormone release
and stuff, women mostly forget a lot of that pain until it
happens again.
Right.
That that's not like, it hurts.
It's that everything that that entails.
watching your child live in this world that you and your husband have created.
And having to see the danger they're in and see them suffer and see those things.
And this is why this is what lies behind sort of theologically
St. Simian's statement to the Theotokos about a sword piercing
heart also. This is key to the the Church's understanding which goes back at
least to say Irenaeus of Leone. So we're talking about second-second century of
the Theotokos as the second Eve. Right? That she sort of as the mother of
Christ feels it a very pointed way as he sees as she sees what the world that she
and the rest.
of humanity have created what that does to her son, what that does to her God, right?
That she experiences, that she experiences that pain, which is like a sword piercing
her heart.
So that I think is a better and more sort of full orb picture, right?
And if you're a woman without biological children, right, adopted children, just people you love,
right?
People who are family seeing that.
I think that's a more full or picture of what's going on there in the tax and what it's
pointing to.
Does that make sense, Georgia?
Well, yeah, that's very helpful.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
Thank you very much for calling.
All right.
Well, we've cleared off our callers.
So we're going to roll on with the second half of this episode.
We're scared of the case.
We scared them off.
Actually one person in the YouTube chat said they called and then pinicked and then hung
I'm sorry.
So, obviously Mike is really scary.
Who knows how badly I'll roast you when your call gets put through.
Just as long as you're not 100% confidence and zero percent knowledge, yes.
I will hurt your feelings with my words people.
Beware.
Yeah.
So, all right.
speaking of Hebrews and we left us at that big
Cliff hanger that dire cliff hanger. That's right. That's right of
Uh-oh
Intentional or deliberate or willful or purposeful sids aren't forgiven by Christ in the New Testament either
According to Hebrews 10 verse 26. Well, let's let's read that in context. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. Well Hebrews 10
Read reading verses 26 through 30
Thank you.
If we go on sinning deliberately after receiving the knowledge of the truth,
there no longer remains a sacrifice for sins, but a fearful expectation of judgment,
and a fury of fire that will consume the adversaries.
Anyone who has set aside the law of Moses dies without mercy on the evidence of two or three
witnesses. How much worse punishment do you think will be deserved by the one who has trampled
underfoot the Son of God, and has profane the blood of the covenant by which he was sanctified,
and is outraged the spirit of grace.
for we know him who said vengeance is mine. I will repay. And again, the Lord will judge his people.
So yeah, taking a context didn't help. Did it?
You're kind of hoping you know, we read a couple more verses that let you off the hook, right?
Nope.
No sacrifice for deliberate sins.
Just a fearful expectation of judgment and a fury of fire that will consume the adversaries.
By the way, the adversaries are meeting the Satan's.
Tt tt tt tt tt.
So, huh.
Seems like the New Testament uses the exact same language.
about what sins are forgiven by Christ's sacrifice as the Old Testament uses about
sacrificial system in general. So if we think that the old test with sacrificial system only dealt
with whoopsies, then that would mean, according to Hebrews at least, that Christ sacrificed the
forgiveness that comes in Christ only deals with whoopsies and accidental sins. Yeah, like literally
if you've seen on purpose there is no hope for you.
Yes, I have a fever says right there, right?
Yes.
which listeners, you know who you are. So yeah. And it's not just, right? It's not just
Hebrews. But here's what's interesting. Here's what's interesting. I'm not proposing any
kind of conspiracy. I'll point out a lot of our English translations soften a lot of
these texts. Hmm. Even even that Hebrew's text while they're Andrew just read. Their
translation of Hebrew is 10 verse 26 is if we go on sinning deliberately, it is a go on
sinning. What does it literally say? It says, if we sin deliberately, if we sin willfully,
if we sit on purpose after receiving the knowledge of the truth.
Yeah, it's not like there's a certain number of times you have to do it.
Yeah, but our friendly English translator has padded that way. We keep on sitting. I mean,
he's in once a while. He just got a, you know, knocking off at some point. Right. Well,
let's, let's look at exhibit B of this, which is in first John chapter three. Okay. Reading
verses four through six. Everyone who makes a practice of sinning also practices lawlessness,
his lawlessness. You know that he appeared in order to take
way sins and in him there is no sin. No one who abides in him keeps on sinning. No one who
keeps on sinning has either seen him or known him. So is it is it keep on is all that keep on
keeping on in the Greek? Keep on keep it on or making a practice of? Yeah. No. That's not the
original text either. Yes. So what it more literally would say is everyone who sins also
practices lawlessness and then later on in verse 6, no one who abides in
him sins, no one who sins has either seen him or known him. That's what the text says.
Yeah, that's the literal sense of the text. Oh, it's interesting. We looked at so this is we're
reading from the ESV, which normally pretty good, pretty good. But we I looked this up in the
net Bible, which is kind of a wooden translation, but it's got all those great notes. And the net
Bible doesn't do all that.
keep on keeping on. It's very direct. It's very much more literal. Everyone who sins.
Yeah.
So, I think we can see that the very least we don't want unintentional sins in the old or
new testament to be referring to accidental sins. We got at least hope this is referring
to something else.
The good news, eh?
Good news everyone. It does refer to something else.
Yes. Yes. It's not.
And this isn't?
Yeah.
I would say the dichotomy is not between whoops. I didn't mean it. And yeah, I meant it.
Yeah. Oh, I did that on purpose. Oh, I didn't even realize I did that.
Yeah. That's not where this is it doesn't fall in that line. It falls along the lines of
what the Bible calls the high-handed sinner. Well, that's the good. I mean, that's a literal
translation and it shows up that way.
you know, sitting with a high hand is how it shows up in the King James Bible, which is still my favorite in terms of the way that it sounds.
And determining everything else.
What is what is being contrasted with quote unquote unintentional sins or involuntary sins versus the opposite?
Right.
This isn't going to be me retranslating and patting the text.
This isn't going to be ice-eating anything.
We're just going to go.
back to the Torah to see what the Torah means by it and what it can
trust unintentional sins with. Yeah. Yeah. Specifically, we're
going to first go to numbers 15, 27 through 30. Okay. If one person
sins unintentionally, so whatever that means, he shall offer a female
goat a year old person offering and the priest will make a
tonement before the Lord for the person who makes a mistake when he
sins unintentionally to make a tonement for him and he should be
forgiven.
You shall have one law for him who does anything unintentionally for him who is native among the people of Israel and for the stranger who sojourns among them, but the person who does anything with a high hand whether he is a native or a sojourner reviles the Lord and that person shall be cut off from among his people.
Right. So this Texas contrasting the person who sins.
unintense quote unquote unintentionally with the person who sins with their hand held high.
Why would they be hold? It's like it's so so when David decided he's going to commit adultery,
he held his hand up in the air. Yes, he raised his hand because he was sure.
Oh, that's that's a that's an ancient reference right there.
So right and so the imagery of the person sitting with their
hand held high, the idea is that they're taking an oath. Yes.
They're sort of swore to their owning what they're doing, right? Which, I mean, even
even in the United States, when someone's taking an oath, they'll, they do that.
They hold their hand up. Raise your right hand, repeat after me. You know,
but you might say to me, Father Steven, you might say, that's just your
interpretation of what it means to be a high handed center.
Okay, let's go back in
the Torah again. Okay.
Deuteronomy 29 versus 18 through 20. Yep. Yep.
You'll get a little more detail on this person. Okay.
Beware less there be among you a man or woman or clan or tribe whose heart
is turning away today from the Lord our God to go and serve the gods of those
nations. Beware less there be among you a root bearing poisonous and bitter fruit.
one who when he hears the words of this sworn covenant,
blesses him.
and his heart saying, I should be safe, though I walk in the stubbornness of my heart.
This will lead to the sweeping away of moist and dry alike. The Lord will not be willing to
forgive him, but rather the anger of the Lord and his jealousy will smoke against that man,
and the curses written in this book will settle upon him, and the Lord will blot out his name from
under heaven. I love that translation of, does it matter if you're dry? It doesn't matter if you're
I'm so amazed.
I know.
I've all done young old rich poor moistened dry Arizona Southern Louisiana. That would be
moistened. Yeah, you're definitely in the moistened. Yeah, I don't know. I want to know
with that Veeids, but we probably don't have time to jump into that. This is it's a it's
a similar set of imagery right. Yeah, they're in the desert, right? That's it. Okay.
A similar set of imagery to the whole hot cold lukewarm thing in Revelation. Yeah. Yeah.
I mean, this example is someone who's, who has decided and it says in his heart, you know
what?
I'm fine.
Even though I know that I'm stubbornly worshipping idols when I should be worshipping
the one true God.
Yes.
He says, you don't know me.
I do what I want.
Right.
Exactly.
So, right.
Does one is right.
Is it out?
It doesn't, doesn't care.
Right.
He raises his...
Hands in his hair and in the air and raises him like he just don't care.
Yeah.
Because he don't.
He just exactly.
So that's what I handed it into.
The unrepentance center, the center who's willing to kind of take an oath on it.
That is it.
And that is what the Torah is doing.
What the Torah is doing repeatedly is the Torah is forbidding the offering of sacrifices for unrepentant sin.
You cannot go and offer a sacrifice and receive forgiveness for a sin that you have not repented of.
I've hurt you of the sacrifice.
Someone else cannot offer a sacrifice for you to get you forgiveness of a sin that you have not repented of.
Right?
That's not how this works.
It's not how any of this works, right?
And it's not just the Torah that says this.
This principle from the Torah is all through the rest of the Old Testament.
Hmm. Right?
So, for example, Psalm 51 or in the Greek Psalm 50 versus 16 through 19.
This is a famous...
Yes, which I call a reference earlier.
It's all passage.
It's always hard for me to read any translation of this out loud because there's one in my head.
Every Orthodox priest has this in his head.
It's using that door in front.
All right, starting with verse 16,
for you will not delight in sacrifice or I would give it.
You will not be pleased with a burnt offering.
The sacrifices of God are a broken spirit,
a broken and contrite heart of God, you will not despise.
Do good design and your good pleasure,
build up the walls of Jerusalem,
then will you delight in right sacrifices
in burnt offerings and whole burnt offerings,
then bulls will be offered on your altar.
Which I mean, Anash said earlier,
it's like, well, you know, what about in the word?
says in the song, you know, let's-
Sacrifices of God are broken, spirit broken, tried, hurtle God, you're not spiced.
For whatever reason, a lot of people, they remember that bit and then forget the last verse,
which says, and then we're going to do sacrifices.
And it's not a metaphor because it talks about like bowls being offered on the altar,
you know, actual animals being sacrificed.
Yeah.
Yeah, this is, this is again, one of those really horrible logic fails.
That's very...
comment from a lot of our evangelical and some of our Protestant friends.
To get that. Oh, sacrifice is your country hard. Right.
Whereas what David is clearly is clearly saying is that after his repentance, right,
God doesn't just want the sacrifice. He wants his repentance.
And then after his repentance, then he will go and offer the sacrifice,
which is exactly what the Torah says you're supposed to do.
And by the way, David is here saying he...
is going to offer sacrifices for things he did on purpose.
Yeah, and traditionally this previously,
Psalm is held to be his repentance
for the sin with Bathsheba.
Yes.
Yeah.
But yeah, this is the keep reading thing.
It's the same problem with Protestants come to you
and say you shouldn't ask saints to pray for you
because there's one mediator between God
and man, the man Christ Jesus.
And if you just read a
a few more verses, St. Paul says,
therefore I desire that
intersections be made for all men.
Oh, no.
Therefore, because there's one
mediator, that's why St. Paul says to make
intersections.
And they will literally quote you that one
mediator thing to say the exact opposite
of what St. Paul was saying that you shouldn't
ask for intersections.
Right. And so the same thing here,
They're quoting
you this thing that God desires to lightens sacrifice that he wants a
contract double spirit to say the opposite the God no no don't do sacrifice
which is the opposite of what David is saying here if you read a couple more
verses yeah people you can read more than one verse at a time I believe in you
I believe in you.
Ah, so...
Yeah, sacrifice is the last step of repentance.
Okay.
Sacrifice is a meal.
We've talked about sacrifice.
It's a meal of reconciliation.
Right.
You have squashed the beef.
Now you break bread together.
Right.
Repentance is all of the action to make things right that precedes that sacrifice.
that meal. Right? That's what repentance is. So the sacrifice is not in and of itself repentance.
The sacrifice becomes the sacrifice performs its function of reconciliation because of your repentance.
Right.
And so in keeping with what David is saying here,
we've mentioned, I think I've only ever done it,
it vague terms actually of this show.
Although there's a lot of this shows.
Oh, did we lose ya?
I'm not sure if you're going to
get it.
Oh, this is like the old days.
Okay. Mike the gatekeeper is
working on bringing
Father Steven back. This is so
exciting. This is like in our
first couple of. I am back.
What happened? Oh, he's back.
Welcome back, Father.
When did I depart? I don't know.
I don't know. I was waiting for
the Mexican radio to begin. I
I don't know you just drove on and on I just
You know, I started chatting with Mike and Simon.
I don't know.
Yeah.
I mean, we were discussing that, um, you know, the meal, the sacrificial meal is the thing
that we are at the end.
Maybe yeah, at the end of, of, um, of the repentance.
So yeah.
Okay.
I cut out there again for a minute.
I don't know if you even know.
Oh, no, I didn't notice.
I didn't notice.
Okay.
But now I think I'm back.
I feel secure.
Okay.
But we're about to quote from the prophets and you know in that moment when you feel secure that is when do disaster will strike
That's it Jeremiah
But yeah, so the meal is the end right and it's the repentance that precedes the meal that makes the meal effective in reconciliation
So father Andrew I wouldn't need you to grunt every about 30 seconds
the rest of the podcast just so I know I'm still connected.
I could just go huh.
Mm-hmm.
Uh-huh.
Huh.
Oh, really?
You could cough lightly.
Anything, anything really.
The chat is wondering if we are, it just says father.
So it could be either you or me.
They want to know if we're tea or coffee guys.
What would you or you, your coffee?
Yeah.
I'm mostly coffee.
You want tea boy?
Wake up and smell the coffee.
I'm mostly coffee, but I do drink tea every so often.
And it's usually Earl Grey, which of course started because of Captain.
and Picard, but when I tasted, I realized I actually liked it.
So, but I never heard of it.
I do drink unsweetened iced tea.
What is cold cold and bitter like my soul?
Unsweeted.
I haven't they deported you yet?
Oh, no, it's I have to go to extreme measures.
Like in East Texas, like down here in Southern Louisiana,
it's not as big a thing.
Right.
But are you serious?
What I lived in East Texas.
Hmm. Oh yeah, everybody down here's licked up all the time.
When I lived in East Texas though, like I had I had the the scam figured out right because if you asked for unsweeted
people would look at you like you were the worst abomination from the pit of hell right I mean so
So what I would do is I would ask for it and then when they started to make the face I would be like I like to add my own
sweetener. Oh
I think they'd be like, oh, okay, okay.
Yeah, you want to get.
I remember so I mean, I'm moving back to North Carolina and honestly, there are certain
certain elements people may not believe this, but there are certain elements of Pennsylvania
cuisine, which I will miss.
However, I know offense Pennsylvania, but I think on balance, North Carolina kind of wins
on this.
And one of the things, of course, that is everywhere there is an almost a restaurant.
You can simply go in and order tea.
And they understand that that means iced and they understand that that means sweet.
such an ex.
that a friend of mine who was from Shelby, North Carolina,
which is not, you know, like the kids from Shelby
go to Gastoni and a party while the kids from Gastoni
are in Charlotte to party, he visited New York City,
he sat down at a restaurant and he ordered tea
and they brought him out a cup of hot water and a tea bag
and he was stumpfounded.
He had no idea what even was even supposed
to do with that equipment at all.
So I don't know which way.
For outsiders perspective, for those of you
who have not spent time in this out,
across the
a vast swath of the American South, when you go into restaurants, they will bring you
a hummingbird feeder as an operative.
That is what happens.
Yeah, no, I drink unsweetened iced tea.
I drink it unsold and bitter.
Yeah, just like your heart.
Yes, exactly.
I want sludge I want syrupy sl-
in the bottom of my team.
It's okay.
What?
Yeah, like if I want to drink coolate,
I just drink coolate.
Okay, like these hybrid drinks.
So, oh, someone in the chat is saying,
don't order sweet tea in Canada.
You'd be sorely disappointed.
I mean, that kind of goes without saying.
Yeah.
And what would you eat with it?
Like sweet tea and poutine?
Like what is even happening here?
Poutine.
Yeah.
Yeah
Any Canadians on the chat tonight?
So I'm feeling reliable with the connection.
So let's soldier ahead.
Okay, okay, okay.
You know I was really cold and bitter.
A lot of the Israelites.
And so that's nice.
Way to youth pastor that one.
Yeah.
We find what we find in the profits, right?
is, well, we find it the problem.
We get to this phase in the history of the Northern Kingdom of Israel, the final phase of their existence, and the Southern Kingdom of Judah, where they are so unrepentant and so advanced in their unrepentant wickedness that God no longer wants sacrifices from them.
God rejects their sacrifices and even tells them through the prophets to stop offering them.
And we refer to this a few times.
of the show in the past in general. But today we're going to actually look at a few of those
passages starting with in Isaiah chapter one. Alrighty. Isaiah chapter one, starting with verse 11.
What to me is the multitude of your sacrifices, says the Lord? I have had enough of burnt offerings
of rams and the fat of wealth at beasts. I do not delight in the blood of bulls or of lambs or of goats.
When you come to appear before me, who is required of you this trampling of my courts? Bring no more
Vain offerings in
sense is an abomination to me. New moon and Sabbath and the calling of convocations, I cannot endure
iniquity and solemn assembly. Your new moons and your appointed feast to my soul hates, they have
become a burden to me. I'm weary of bearing them. When you spread out your hands, I will hide my
eyes from you, even though you make many prayers. I will not listen. Your hands are full of blood.
Yeah, that's cool.
No, the imagery at the end.
You have to imagine that.
The prayer posture that you'll see a lot of Orthodox Christians use during the Lord's Prayer,
where they have their hands held out and sort of cupped. That was already a common prayer posture
at this point. And so the imagery is that they're spreading out their hands to pray in that prayer
posture, but their cupped hands are full of human blood. So it's even more metal than you thought maybe.
And sorry, I don't understand.
Right, and this isn't just the sacrifices, right? This is the sacrifices. This is the Sabbath,
right? This is the feasts that God told them to do, right? He's telling them to stop doing,
right? All of it, right? Because they are unrepent, right? Because they are guilty, they are
high-handed centers, right? They have not repented. And so...
Not only did the sacrifice is not do anything, right?
But doing them anyway, doing them in this hypocritical way, right, is in itself an
abomination before God, is itself a slap in God's face.
to think that somehow he doesn't notice or that somehow you're receiving
forgiveness automatically or whatever it is you're thinking.
Yeah.
This is this is almost a kind of paganize.
You know, your relationship with God.
So but it's not just Isaiah.
Yep.
It's also, for example, Amos.
Amos chapter five, verse 21, I hate.
I despise your feasts and I take no delight in your solemn assemblies,
even though you offer me your burnt offerings and green offerings, I will not accept
them.
And the peace offerings of your fat and animals, I will not look upon them.
take away from me the noise of your songs to the melody of your harps.
I will not listen, but like justice rolled down like waters and righteousness like an ever
flowing stream.
It's interesting.
It's not just sacrifices doesn't want.
He's also not interested in, you know, songs and music.
So the people think this is all up like it's an anti-irritable thing.
Well, you better stop singing in church too, you know?
Now you yeah, and feel free.
If you see the local worship team, just hit him with aimas.
523. I have a request. Could you sing that song? It's Amos 523. It says take away from
me the noise of your songs. Yeah. But yeah, verse 24 there, let Justice Roldale, like
Waters and Regis is like an everflowing stream, gets used all the time politically. You know
What's odd? I've never heard that used politically in the cut
text of disingenuous worship. Yeah. Yeah. And it could be. I mean, you could you could craft a
politically like America claims to be a Christian nation, but we're unrepentantly wicked, right? I mean,
you could you could that's a launching point for something, right? But yeah, that's usually not how
it's quoted, right? But so what's the idea that justice is really like what is saying? What? Justice,
the correct order of things.
You need to repent. You need to put things right. Okay? That's what you need to do first.
Then come and celebrate the Feasts. Then come and bring me the sacrifices. Then come and sing me the Psalms.
Right? After the repentance has happened. Okay? So the sacrifices don't magically do the repentance for you.
Yeah, the
repentance comes first, right? Then the worship.
More on this theme from Jeremiah. Okay. Who was not a bullfrog, at least not this one.
Cheeriest. One of the cheeriest books in the Bible. Okay. Jeremiah chapter seven,
starting with verse 21, thus says the Lord of hosts that God of Israel,
add your burnt offerings to your sacrifices and eat the flesh. For in the day that I brought them
out of the lane of Egypt. I did not.
not speak to your fathers or command them concerning burnt offerings and sacrifices, but
this command I gave them, obey my voice and I will be your God and you shall be my people
and walk in all the way that I command you that it may be well with you.
Now this is an interesting one.
Works righteousness.
Because if you stop at the end of verse 22, you'd be awful confused.
The day I brought them out of the letter of each of my did not speak to your fathers
the command them concerning board offices and sacrifices.
Look.
Like he literally did.
Hmm.
Right.
Okay, so how do we understand this?
He literally did.
Yeah.
Right. The point that's being made here is not
God never wanted sacrifices for them at all.
Yeah, there's just an order.
The point was yes.
What did I tell you?
I told you I wanted you to live in this way.
And those sacrifices and stuff.
were part of living in that way, right? But they're not a replacement for it, right?
Offering sacrifices, right? Seeking regular forgiveness is not a substitute for repentance.
It is not the same thing as Repentance.
Right, Repentance.
is getting things back in order, recommitting to following in God's ways, making
the reparations you need to make. Right? Making the amends you need to make,
doing the things you need to make up for what you've done, then, right? Then the
sacrifices, then the worship, then those things have their part. You make things
right first in your worship. It's almost like, you know what Christ said.
You're on your way
To give your offering you realize someone has something against you you stop you make that right first
Then you go and offer the
Saga Fies
Right it's almost like this is remarkably consistent through the whole Bible
huh
Almost and speaking of the whole Bible
If you got one of them Protestant Bibles,
last book of the Old Testament, Malachi.
All right, Mark I, chapter 1, starting with verse 10,
O that there were one among you who would shut the doors, that you might not kindle fire on my altar in vain.
I have no pleasure in you, says the Lord of hosts, and I will not accept an offering from your hand,
for from the rising of the sun to its setting, my name will be great among the nations.
And in every place incense will be offered to my name and a pure offering, for my name will be great among the nations says the Lord of hosts.
So is this a contrast like Israel's not doing it right but the nations are gonna be doing it? Is that the idea here?
Well, yeah, so the verse 10 is talking about like I
Wish one of you would just go to the temple and shut it all down
Yeah, right lock the doors
Turn out the lights, right. It's over
right
but
Right
The Lord is going to be worshiped
truly worshiped by the nations, right, prophetically, right. But that's going to follow the
set, right, the idea, the implication is that's going to follow the same order, meaning the nations
are going to repent. It's not that the nations are going to continue to be idolatrous, it's
sexually immoral and keep doing all the things they're doing. At the time, Malachi has written,
They're just going to start off for exacrifices to Yahweh.
So it'll be all good, right?
No, that's the problem with Judah, right?
Yeah.
It's that they're going to actually repent,
and then come an offer worship, right?
And this is one of the very early,
you get some more of this in the New Testament,
this jealousy idea that God brings the other nations
to repentance in order to provoke Judah to jealousy
jealousy so that they will also repent.
the goal is that they would repent as well, right? And return to worship. God, it's also
interesting to me though that a lot of our evangelical friends will say things like if possible,
if it makes sense, you should always interpret biblical passages literally. We're all about
literal interpretation of the Bible.
Not on the floor.
Which is why they're, let's say which is
which is why they're all using incense in their services.
Right, exactly.
But somehow when we get to Malachi, Chapter 1, verse 11,
in every place incense will be offered to my name and a pure offering.
Uh, the whole offering incense and offering a sacrifice everywhere.
Uh, well that, I mean, it's clearly just a matter of that.
That can't be literal.
Yeah.
I mean, you got to have allegory for some passages.
Right.
like
really this is the one. Yeah. So, so why are we going through this? Well, where we've
arrived at here is that the sacrificial system and the Old Testament, Old Testament religion,
the religion of ancient Israel, right? Was never transactional. It was never sort of mechanical.
Yeah, you couldn't just sort of buy forgiveness by offering the right sacrifice.
Right.
It was never this system where you plug in certain inputs, you get the same outputs no matter
what.
Right.
Because like in the profits, Father Andrew just read, right?
The people of Israel and Judah are continuing to put in the same inputs.
Right.
And God is saying, you're not going to get the outputs you want.
the results you get for the
those inputs are no longer going to be good. In fact, they're going to be exactly what
you don't want. Right? So it was never this transactional mechanical system. Right? And
that was the point that these distinctions that we've been talking about, like quote unquote
involuntary sin. That's what these distinctions were aimed at. We're aimed at breaking the
idea for the Israelites that God or
salvation or faithfulness, religion, whatever label you want to put on it.
They're almost all kind of a little bit anachronistic.
But whatever label you want to put on that, that was not mechanical, right?
Breaking that idea in their terms, you know,
they didn't have a lot of mechanisms, but in their time,
but for them, it would have been more magical.
The idea that, you know, you do the correct
in-cantation or do the correct thing and it produces this result,
automatic.
right, but for us mechanical, it was breaking and shattering that idea. And so in the forthcoming
third half, we're going to talk about hey, if we've now learned from the whole Bible by
looking at the sacrificial system that faithfulness to God is not...
something. True religion is not something that's mechanical and transactional.
Does anybody affect on any other parts of theology? Well, on that second cliffhanger,
we're going to take our second and final break and we'll be right back. Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your
calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-235-
4-6.
That's 855 AF Radio.
Elizabeth has a problem.
She wants to pray in church more than anything, but every time she tries to pray her feet start
tapping.
How can she pray if she can't stand still?
When a dragon appears on the monastery's land and the only solution is prayer, Elizabeth
worries even more.
turns to the end.
the sands for help. Through their guidance and intercession, Elizabeth learns that our whole bodies
have a place in prayer, and sometimes our spiritual weaknesses can be a gift that God uses for great good.
This wonderfully fun story, illustrated to capture the hearts of busy children,
was inspired by the life of the 6th century saint Elizabeth the Wonderworker.
You can find a St. Sky to pray with your feet at store.AncientFaith.com.
That's store.AncientFaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Hey, is that the first children's book that has ever been advertised on this show?
which is ironic since the show is not for children. But it was a children's book about a dragon.
So, I mean, we do have a new producer that is less prone to the salty language.
Shall we say? That's true. Sayler Talk. So it is a little more
more than it used to be made. That's right. That's right.
Exactly.
Let's all give up. Have a moment to
of sadness that we no longer have
truly the tank character on board.
Oh well.
So but we are getting we are getting
a caller.
So is this the coward from the chat
or is it?
I don't.
Don't call it.
I finally found a sparring.
Yeah, no, this is we've got
a William of Tennessee.
So William of Tennessee, I don't know if Mike,
Oh, did you just hang-
William or Mike just hung him up. See, look at that. I'm looking at the call board and just disappears.
Now, wait, he might be back. He might be back. So exciting. The anticipation. Are you there? William.
What is to get doing over there, man? He's dropping me. He's dropping collars. Get it together, man.
Well, sorry, William. How are you there? I am. Can you hear me, Father? Yes, we hear you. Welcome. Welcome.
I'm just one of those people who called in just to say,
Dieto, but was missed in the second half.
No, actually, the question actually came up in the,
this end of the second half in regards to the offering of incense,
and how that relates to the sacrificial system.
So it's been reiterated multiple times that a sacrifice is a meal
that's consumed in
seems to be an interesting place. I'm not aware of anywhere in the old
testament that incense is used as a sin offering, but at the very least the pagans
tried to force Christians to offer incense sacrifices to the gods even though
incense isn't quite a meal, but also we have the incense that we will
since the icons with and we see that as something different than the sacrifice of the Eucharist.
So what the heck is going on with instant sacrifice?
What is going on? Well, I mean, if you look at the sacrifices in the old covenant,
then you'll notice there's a pattern between the eaten sacrifices and the incense sacrifice.
And that is that and correct me if I get any of this wrong father.
I'm just
going from memory here, that is that the various kinds of sin offerings and so forth are offered
so that those doing that offering are purified so that incense can be offered.
There's a purifying effect of the sin offerings and so forth so that the incense can be offered
to God. Right? So that's, and the instances offered on the ins
the actual tent, whereas the other sacrifices are offered outside of that holy of
holies. And then of course, you know, that maps also into the temple when that's built.
Is that all correct, Father? Am I getting that right?
The words of the late great Charlie Murphy. Wrong. No, man.
I thought it was right. Well, I don't know what was weird.
Like there are a couple of things.
So like incense wasn't offered in the Holy of Holy,
incense was offered in the Holy Place.
Okay.
That's where the altar of incense was.
All right.
Okay.
And that was the baseline.
So the incense offering was the baseline.
That commandment comes earlier than the sacrifices.
Okay.
And so that happens at morning and evening, okay?
Yes.
Like best presenter or throws.
Right.
And so in turn.
of the offering of incense, right, we're burning something and the smoke is rising. You have to think
of it in terms of like a whole burnt offering, a sacrifice, an animal sacrifice that's a whole
burnt offering. How is that given to God? It is burnt, the smoke arises to God and the scriptures
describe God's receiving of it as a sweet fragrance in His nostrils, right? So the idea is through
through the cement.
that God is receiving it. We even say this, we say this in the liturgy.
Maybe unless you're at a parish where the liturgy they skip the litany before the Lord's prayer.
But if they don't, one of the petitions we talk about the Eucharist in those terms,
actually. We talk about Christ receiving the Eucharist as a savor of spiritual sweetness.
or in a row.
in our more recent translations.
Oh, they changed to a robot.
Before that, it was odor.
Oater, yeah, I know.
I know.
I think it changed it to saver.
And now I guess it's a robot.
Romas better.
Yeah.
But, but so there's that language.
So you can see how that there's a direct parallel
there with the incent, right?
We offer the incents to God.
Okay.
So the purificatory thing is actually after the fact,
not before the fact.
Okay.
So
When we are offering incense in the Orthodox Church,
the priest says the prayer of offering the incense,
which is incense we offer the O Christ our God
as a savor of spiritual sweetness, receive it upon the
most holy and ideal turn, send down and return upon us
the grace of the I know Holy Spirit.
Right.
I'm doing for memory, but I've kind of done that
a few thousand times literally now.
Pretty close.
That's it.
Right.
So, so we're offering, right, when we're sensing the icon of a saint, or we're sensing a human, right?
We're sensing the bishop or clergy or lay any.
We're not offering the incense to them.
Right.
No, it's offered to God.
That prayers, the offering of incense, we're offering the incense to Christ.
So that's the worship element.
We're offering the incense to Christ as a savior of spiritual sweetness as we say in the prayer, right?
Thank you.
But the offering in the offering, the process of burning it, it produces smoke.
And so within all sacrificial ritual, this is another thing that parallels animal sacrifice.
Once the thing has been offered as a gift, right, to the divine.
So I'm just talking about sacrificial ritual in general now.
The byproduct of that offering is seen as holy.
And in being holy, it now has purificatory effect.
So in the case of animal sacrifices,
like the goat free, the sin offering on the day of atonement,
that is the blood.
You have the blood that is the byproduct
drain when you're offering the animal to go.
The blood has now become sacred
and that blood can now be used to purify the sanctuary.
Right or the case
of the synopherex of Leviticus 4, that blood is smeared, that word smeared there is
conferr, right?
Porra atonement.
The atonement, yeah.
On the altar, right?
It's used to purify the altar, and then the rest is poured out, right?
So in the same way, with incense, you don't have, incense doesn't produce blood, it produces
smoke.
And so the smoke, because the incense has been offered to Christ, it has now left the
realm of the profane into the realm of the sacred.
And now the smoke is made holy by it being incense being offered to God.
That smoke now has purificatory effects.
And so when we sense things with the smoke,
the smoke has the purifying effect because it is the smoke generated by incense
that has been offered to Christ.
Okay.
That's it.
All right.
So when then what is the significance of the fact that like animals are offered further
out and the incense kind of further in in the tabernacle of the temple?
Because you can't do a whole burn offering inside a tent.
Hmm.
Okay.
So it's in the courtyard.
Got you.
All right.
William, does that does that cover it?
Well, I think so.
So incense is a sacrifice.
It is consumative.
offer to Christ, but we do.
don't use it as a sin offering we use blood because life isn't the blood is that about right?
Right. Right. Yeah. It's not consumed though. Like incense is not consumed. It's not eaten.
Well, it's consumed by via the nose. Yeah. I mean, right. Yeah. In the same way that God could,
it's consumed by the fire technically. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I mean, and it's within,
And it's within, like, it's all within this matrix of how
hospitality, right? That's what's going on in sacrifice is this sense of hospitality being offered. But yeah, incense offering is not a sin offering. Yeah, it is a different type of offering.
Yeah. Thank you.
All right, thank you very much for calling.
We have, we actually have the caller who called in and panicked and hung up.
So it's David from Minnesota.
David.
Welcome to Laura Spirit's podcast. Have you removed the yellow streak from your back, sir?
I'm not. I'm okay. Frozen in shock.
Yeah, well you already been a soda, so I would expect you to be frozen about now.
Oh yeah, it's frigid. It's frigid outside. There's ice everywhere up there.
I'm very happy. Yep. So what's on your mind? So I come from a like
like pedicostle background.
with a guy who has a glutton for Martin Luther and Talvin,
like our pastor, which has bred them a lot.
So he loved the whole,
that's the one to do this thing.
And you guys are kind of talking a little bit of the same thing
at the beginning, right?
PSA, I think that's what you should just tell me.
It's hard to get out of your head,
but I just had a single question about specific verse
in Psalm 87 in the text,
Son of Gustin and St. S and Asius interpret,
Now I try.
I just realized that my brain is not smart enough
to comprehend what they're saying.
But 820 says, in verse 8,
the Palm Me has by Nanger Fix itself
and all that way has to end to me.
They data apply that to Jesus.
I didn't understand how it worked in the sense of like,
I know that it's not, you know,
if Wrath in Orthodox theology is approaching glory,
unwardingly, Christ can't be unwardly.
So I just wanted to hear you guys to sense
on what that means.
how that applies to Christ. Okay. Alright, so that's, yes, I'm 87 and sub two
agent and 88 in the Hebrew numbering. What's going on there, father? We are
going to actually talk about Pinot substitute, substitutionary atonement and
all of that in the third half. So you are tracking with us. There was no need
to run away. We were already with you. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I mean, I've read
it's all there's even this dissertation I watched.
I've listened to the atonement episode, like the priesthood episode, like multiple times,
trying to get this in my head.
I'm just, you know, I just taught this from when I was like, to, to when I was like 22.
So it's sure, sure.
Yeah, it's well, you know, put it in your head as a grid and then you read everything
else through it.
Yeah.
And the immortal words of a great poet from nearby Reading Pennsylvania, shake it off, shake
it off.
So what's up with all that with all that father see why though?
Yes, so I mean what so what they're doing is their proof texting right they're just trying to say
Ah see here's a verse that says
Christ experienced God's wrath
sort of
If you read it read it
Yeah, you know certain
kind of right
right um
But so the wrath is not just defined as experiencing God's holiness unworthily.
Right. God's holiness, when experience unworthily, is experienced as wrath. That is a correct statement.
But this is using Rath in a different sense.
And that sense is related to the idea.
And if you want more on this, go back to our episode on blessings and curses, that we have this idea in our head of blessings and curses being this sort of very external thing.
Right. So you do the things God wants you to do and so he blesses you or you do the things God doesn't want you to do and so he curses you.
And that's not really
what's going on with the way the Bible talks about being in a state of
blessedness or being in a state of being cursed or anathema. And so essentially
to do the short version, being blessed means that you are living your life in
a way that isn't accord with God's justice, meaning the order within creation.
that you have aligned yourself correctly with God with your fellow human being.
with creation in such a way that is being in a blessed state. Right? Justice is when everything is in its proper place working correctly. That includes you.
Right.
And working together in harmony includes you.
be going to a cursive state, right?
Means that you are at odds with, right?
You're trying to move it a different...
direction. You're going against the grain, right? Kind of in the bad religion sense. You're, right,
you're, you're trying to move into a different direction. You are, and therefore you're at odds
with your fellow man. You're at odds with God. You're at odds with the creation itself around you.
Right. And that because of the order of creation, inevitably produces destruction and chaos,
Right
And that's why you're in this cursed state.
And God's wrath is often used,
for example, in Romans one, it's used in this way,
to describe a person who is in that state, right?
There are different ways you, so for example,
if you were describing that person who's in that cursed state,
if you're describing their relationships with other humans, right?
You might say they're at war with other humans,
they're at war with their brother, they hate their brother.
They're jealous of their brother. They're bitter toward their, they're all these words you'd use,
right? To describe the relationships between them and other people
while in that state. Or if you're describing their relationship to
the material world around them like the created order, right? They're various ways you can
describe it. And one of the ways in which that person's relationship with God is described
is that they are under God's wrath.
Right, that they're experiencing and and God's wrath is not this external thing where it's like God's mad at you and so he's throwing fire from heaven or something.
Right. God, when he talks about his wrath in the scriptures of the prophets, even in Romans one, when St. Paul is talking about it, he talks about it in terms of nature itself.
So think about when Moses talks about this.
to the astronomy when the people are going into the land, he says, the land itself, right?
The wasps, the bees, right? The animals, right? They're all going to fight with you against
the giant clans because of their wickedness, right? Or think about in the last few
Psalms, right? The wind, the rain, the lightning is going to come against you, right? Like nature
itself will turn, will turn against you and your wickedness. So when we understand
That's all this is to get your questions.
Readers.
that Salomon persona Christy, right, meaning that this is in some way reflective of the experience
of Christ, Christ though he did not have any of the wickedness or sin, right, that would normally
bring this state about for someone. He experienced that, not just in his death, but in his life
Right? His life on her, he was rejected. Right? He was homeless. He...
was traveling for place to place. He was mocked by people. He was disbelieved by people.
All of this leading up to eventually his suffering, his humiliating and torturous death,
right? All of these things that happened to him. So, and this is the way St. Paul talks
about Christ being, right, a curse it incursent is everything that hangs on a tree. Christ
experienced the results of that, the fruit of that, right?
Even though he
He had not sinned, he had not contributed to the evil, the corruption of the world, but
he experienced its effects nonetheless.
And so God's wrath there is being described compared to the waves of the sea towards the
floodwaters.
Christ experienced what that is like for the worst of sinners.
though he was.
without sin while he was on earth, right? So the problem here with PSA is not that, yes, Christ
suffered obviously unjustly, because he was righteous and he suffered the fate of the unrighteous,
right? No one disputes that. The question is whether he did that instead of you. That's the
with Pedal Substitution.
Well, that's the question of substitution is whether he did that instead of you and then
Petyl substitution in particular is, is all of that a punishment from God and external
punishment from God rather than just the consequence of the world?
Because a big part of what's going on in the case of Christ is that there's this inversion
happening, right?
suffers that state not because the world is just a
and the creation is in the beautiful order
in which God created it, and he is wicked,
it's an inversion of that.
God's creation has become so corrupt
and twisted and unjust and out of order
that when Christ, as the righteous one,
enters into it, he is completely at odds with it.
Right, so it is a parallel experience,
but actually an inversion of that experience.
But the question, and we'll get into this a little as we continue in this half is, is that
substitutionary?
Is Christ doing that so you don't have to, right?
Is he doing that instead of you?
And then also how does that relate to the idea of external punishment?
Yep.
Does that make sense?
Yeah.
So I just want to literally like two seconds to reach.
The glory is not always.
going, right, no, not going. Wrath is not always experiencing God's glory unworthily. It can
also just being at odds with creation in some sense. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. Cool. So, okay, that
actually explains a lot. Yeah. And Romans, Romans one is a good place to go over that. The
Saint Paul starts with now the wrath of God is revealed from heaven against all the wickedness
a man, and he goes on to talk about the unnatural acts.
that the Gentiles have been committing, right?
It turns a sexual immorality idolatry.
Right, okay, that makes sense.
Yep.
That puts a lot of things in place for me.
So that's the idea of like the whole,
he gave them over to their unnatural desires.
That's the intent to wrap,
even though he's not doing it.
Right, he gave them what they thought they wanted
as a punishment.
Yep, yep.
Well, thank you very much for...
for regaining your courage, David, and calling in from the girded up your lines frozen north.
So all right. It's the third half.
Yeah. Well, let's talk about substitute area atonement. I mean, we basically kind of laid out how
the whole sacrificial system is not actually transactional. And so therefore,
salvation, yeah, salvation is not transactional.
either. So yeah, let's talk about
substitutionia tomen and all the various kinds of.
I don't know, it's sort of the stuff that needs to be,
the brambles need to be swept clear, I think from a lot of
minds of West.
Of things. Yeah. Yeah.
So, yeah, so salvation, not transactional, right?
and this is one of the
core problems with the idea of substitutionary atonement of any kind.
I said we'd come back to this.
Right?
Because sometimes you get these guys,
they're my brothers and sisters in Christ.
They're Orthodox Christians.
Who say things like, well, we don't believe in penal substitution,
but we do believe in substitution.
And that doesn't mean anything.
Really doesn't mean anything.
Yeah.
And also sometimes, frankly,
It's based on translations of...
Church fathers that are not done by Orthodox Christians and are done by people who have
other theology that is not compatible with Orthodox theology.
Yes.
If you come at me with a bunch of quotes from the Church fathers from Shaaf, I'm going
to point out to you that Shaaf, in a particular point of view, right?
But yeah, I've started asking this question a lot when you get these people trying to
proof-text church fathers, right? But they'll say like...
and it's proof-textic because we all look see he used the word wrath or oh look he used the word
propitiation or oh look he used the word punishment right my response to that is I guarantee you that
church father did not use any of those words because he was not writing in English right exactly
right so there's there's some other word behind there we have to look at that word and we have to
look at how that father uses that word before we can even have this discussion right um and so
Oh.
Most of the people, frankly, trying to have that discussion
can't have that discussion,
because they're monolingual Americans.
Yeah, sorry.
Right?
Like, at a certain point,
and this is gonna make me sound like an arrogant jerk,
but what else is new?
And I don't care.
I don't care.
Okay, look, at some point you have to accept
if you only know English,
and you can only read the church fathers
the Bible in turn.
translation. You are going to have to at some point find some people who actually know the original
languages who you trust and just believe them about what it says. Yeah. Okay. You are not equipped.
You don't have to go and learn those languages. But if you're not going to go and learn those
languages, you're not entitled to an opinion on this. You aren't. You can't have one. You're not
capable of doing the work to develop an informed opinion on it.
So you have to believe someone who does have an informed opinion.
You don't get to loan range of this.
If you want to go and do the work and learn the language and study, and study that church
father and how he uses that word and do that, great dissertation topic, good.
That's a great thing to do.
We need more people doing that.
But if you're not going to do that, shut up.
Shut up on social media.
Stop causing trouble.
Stop trying to cause factions in the church.
You
That's a sin. That's a grievous sin. Okay. Just stop. You're not a teacher. Stop trying
to be one. You have to learn before you can teach. If you don't want to learn, cool.
Please be with you. But don't try and teach. Okay. Minor rant on. Address your comments
on what an arrogant jerk I am to father Andrew and ancient faith that come.
So...
Yeah, but no, so the and that's not the people I was just writing about are not the people who say we believe in
substitution, but not penal substitution. Let me be clear. Those are
nice good-hearted people
worst thing they're guilty of is some very soft ecumenism. They're trying to they're trying to throw the other people the
bone, right?
Maybe I could come with you a little ways, but you can't just
Because the core of the idea of substitution, right?
really ultimately in terms of the New Testament,
this comes down to the preposition, e-Pair.
And whether you translate that as an idea like instead of
or in place of, or if you translate that as in behalf of
or with benefit toward.
Right.
And when you read the New Testament, the church fathers
and they're using that in terms of Christ and his death,
They don't use it to mean instead of, or in place of.
They use it to mean in behalf of or for the benefit of.
Right.
So, people will say that some of these people even proof text
to quote that just says like Christ's died for our sins.
Well, for there can mean a lot of different things.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Right.
died for our sins, doesn't mean
our sins made us worthy of death and he died instead of us necessarily. Doesn't
necessarily mean that, right? Even if you think it means that, it doesn't necessarily
mean that. It can equally mean he died in behalf of us.
Right? He died on our behalf in order to purify us from our sins, for example.
Yep. Right. So those are possible meanings. Once you have possible meanings, you then
Find means to.
decide, right, what the actual meaning is out of those possible meanings. But so let's
take a look at this idea. This whole substitution idea is a transaction by definition. Right?
It's a transaction. And in the case of Christ's death, so it's a term that's a substitutionary
atonement now. And so any kind of substitutionary atonement is a view of atonement that views
atonement as being about Christ.
death. That in itself is a problem. We're not going to go into that right now. Yeah, I mean,
I mean, let's do everything is what episode? No, just as a sidebar like what is a tonement
goes here at tone in episode, right? You know, called the priest. So a tone that involves
a lot more than only Christ's death, right? Yeah. But any substitute when anybody's talking
about substitute, sorry, atonement, that's what they're talking about. Right? No one uses
this substitute, you're showing a tone.
to say, Christ lived through childhood and adolescence so that you don't have to. Right.
So any kind of atonement view that's based on like recapitulation, like you find in St.
Irenaeus or St. Athanasius, obviously is not substitutionary. Right. Where Christ lived
through all the phases of human life and thereby purified them. Right. Clearly that's not
instead of you.
Right.
That's, um.
But so that's why we say you de facto isolate the idea of Atomit to Christ's death when you do this.
Now as we've talked about a bunch on this show, this is a distinction that's found all through the Church Vathers, but as with a lot of things, it is precise exposition of the Orthodox faith, say John of Damascus lays this out very clearly.
Right? That there is physical death and there is spiritual death.
And this distinction is critically important for a whole bunch of things. That's why we keep bringing it up on the show.
Hey, physical death is the separation of the soul from the body.
Spiritual death is the separation of the soul from God.
We need to be very clear. And this is why we can't believe in any kind of penal substitutionary atonement.
Right?
Any kind of penal substitutionary atonement requires Christ to have died a spe-
spiritual death. Which means that he was damned or that his human soul was separated from God.
His human soul is separated from God, which means either like there's two ways, or you could go
for both actually, there's two ways to be utterly heretical about this. You know, there's,
there's, you can be an historian, you know, or actually maybe a Paulinarian, I don't know,
you know, or you can mess up your
trinitarian theology.
Yeah, right. So either happy to have God the Son being separated from God the Father or
Gods you break the Trinity or Jesus the man separated from Christ God right Christ humanity is separated from his divinity in which case
You're probably an historian or William Lee and Craig in a Paul and Aryan
Right, so so he literally says this in his book. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, believes it peels up some judiciary atonement
Because again, fracked really wrong.
to be wrong about everything. So yes, so if you're going to say that that you know Christ died so
that we don't have to, if you're going to accept that it's Christ died spiritual death, then you
have basically entered into deeply heretical zone. Right. If you're going to say that is what
Peter substitute Sherry atonement is, right? He's saying that Christ died a spiritual death
so that we don't have to. Now the other way you can say
Well, he died a physical death so that we don't have to,
but I've done way too many funerals to believe that.
Right.
Christ did die a physical death.
Christ was a physical death.
His human soul was separated from his human body,
but it was not so that we wouldn't have to
because we're all gonna die,
except for those who are still gonna die a physical death.
Yeah, right.
So clearly that didn't work.
You know, if that's what was going on.
So that is it, that is it work.
People propose that sometimes but I don't think they've thought it through
About the fact that I still physically die so then there's not a substitution there
Right there's there can't be a
Substituted but also by the way I just want to hammer this home
This is why the the argument sometimes advanced by Muslims and some Unitarians
How can God die?
This is why that argument is stupid.
Yeah, I mean again, you are in this story.
And that is what it is.
Die.
Yeah.
Well, no, no, with them, it's because die means what we say, Christ died.
What do we say?
God died on the cross, which we do say.
What do we mean?
We mean that his human soul was separated from his human body.
Right.
He had a physical death, a material death.
So any Muslim or unitarian who wants to explain to me how if God took a human soul and human
body. He...
could not possibly separate the two of them.
Can't come explain that to me.
Otherwise, your how can God die argument is stupid.
It's stupid because yeah, both,
I hate to tell you, but both Muslims and Unitarians
believe in an afterlife,
meaning neither of them think die means cease to exist.
Die for that means the same thing it means for me.
human soul is separated from your human body. So their argument is stupid. It makes no sense.
Right? It's just an incoherent, therr, right? Like no one should take that seriously.
And I mean that literally. I mean, if someone makes that argument to you, laugh at them.
Then explain why it's dumb. That you should laugh first. You should. Because that's the only way
we're going to get them to stop saying that dumb thing is public shaming. It's a powerful tool.
Anyway...
St Gregory Polymos summarizes the actual Orthodox view very well. He says that Christ by his physical death
He uses the terms physical and spiritual death like St. John does
Yeah Christ by his physical death
Takes away both our physical and spiritual death
Right
We how does he take away our physical
not by us, not dying, right? So see the substitution doesn't work. Christ dies
physically and because of Christ's physical death, he takes away our physical
death, how in the resurrection, right? Our soul, our body, reunited. And how does
he take away our spiritual death, not by dying a spiritual death. He only dies
a physical death, but he takes away our spiritual death in that our souls are
reunited to God. Our human souls are reunited to God. Because our human
humanity is united to God in Christ's person.
To show you how clueless
some of these penal substitution guys are online,
these crypto-pronestants,
I have seen them quote this from St. Gregory Polymas
as if it proves penal substitution.
Wow.
Those are the people I was telling earlier to shut up.
They're literally posting quotes that refute their position
as if they saw.
support their position, that's how little they understand what they're talking about.
Okay.
Am I potentially embarrassing people and being mean to them?
Yes, because they need to repent and stop doing what they're doing.
They are causing factions within the church.
It's online, so it's only semi-real, but it's still factions.
They're confusing people.
Yeah.
And it needs to stop.
Thank you.
Yeah, I mean, you know, if the fact that pretty much any clergyman who responds to you
about these kinds of things says, no, we do not believe in penal substitute, shared
to them. That is wrong. That is false. If you know better than everyone else, all the
leadership of the church that actually bothers to respond to you about this, then maybe
you're the one that's wrong. You know, like because orthodoxy has actual authority.
you
And if you're the one restoring the gospel, you kind of sound more like Joseph Smith
than you do like one of the church fathers.
You know, if you got to restore the gospel, anyway.
Where were we?
Yes, what about repentance father Steven?
about, well, we have to do that. If, right, Jesus, if this is
institutionary, right? What? Yeah. Why is there? Why is there
repentance of the Torah if the sacrificial system? Right? We
already talked about that a little bit. If that was
substitutionary, right? But there's stuff about
repending all through the New Testament. Let's just talk about
the New Testament. Oh, repent. Yeah, for the kingdom of God
that is literally repaid.
the gospel is summarized when it's first being preached. Right. What must I do to be saved?
They say it acts repent. They possibly say repent and be baptized. Yeah. Yeah. Repent and believe
in the Lord Jesus. Right. Which we repent and repentant. But what is repair and what is repentance?
It's it's been defined by the you know thousands of years of is really tradition up to that point.
It doesn't just mean stop sinning and don't do it anymore.
That's not all the repentance is.
Yes, stop.
Don't do it anymore, but there are actually specific actions of repentance that have to be taken.
But so just like it doesn't make any sense to say, right, we talked about this with
in terms of like stealing the ox, right?
Well, if you believe that the sacrificial system is substitutionary, then well, the thing
Then you killed took the penalty for that sin, which was apparently...
death, but it's now apparently also making restitution. But we talked about how that makes
no sense. But that same dynamic happens, right, within sorry guys, evangelicalism especially.
Right. But it's some other forms of process too, that accept penal substitution that
It obviates repentance, meaning like Christ paid the penalty for that sin.
They'll frequently say.
All my sins pass present future.
What's I haven't even done yet? He's already paid the price for them. So what does it mean for me to repent? I mean and
and like that's what you just said is not I mean for some it it is probably something of a caricature
But I can tell you that within the kind of evangelicalism I was raised with and it was not some weird little sect
I was part of kind of mainstream Baptistish evangelicalism
It was why they all had AK-47s at the church services, but exactly those other than that.
Pretty amazing.
Yeah.
It was absolutely taught.
You should live a good life, but if you had this moment of sincere repentance, and we'll
talk about some of this in a second here, and if you had this moment where you turned
around, you said, you know, I'm lost in my sins.
Jesus is Lord of my life I place on.
all my hope in you, if you get saved, then nothing you do after that can change your
eternal destiny.
Like it was described this way to me.
It was preached by many preachers in that world that you could go live a life of sin
after that and you would still go to heaven when you die.
Now some of the better ones would also say, but if you do go live in that life of sin,
and that proves.
You never really met it. Yeah. You know, but but there was this idea of like it doesn't matter what
you do after that. There's nothing you can do to change it. Yeah. You know, and that was supposed to
be that was supposed to assure you like, oh, you and and you know, I understand what that's reacting to.
It's reacting to this caricature although not completely a caricature, but mostly a caricature
of what they think Roman Catholicism is about, where you're living in this constant anxiety.
like, am I in the state of grace or my out of state of grace or my
state of grace, my out of state of grace?
So I'm gonna hit by a bus on my way to confession and die,
you know, like that sort of sense of, I don't know at any moment,
you know, and so like this was supposed to make you have assurance,
or you know, to put it really in what it really means,
it's to make you feel better so that you don't feel anxious
about all this kind of stuff.
Right.
But even beyond, right?
So you are focusing there mainly on the positive element of
living a good life and doing good things.
Right? But even just focusing for a cent on repentance as such
What does it mean if you believe that Christ paid the penalty for it? What does it mean to repent? Yeah
I mean it kind of means while I feel bad about it. I'm gonna try not to do that again
Yeah, or or or if I do do that again
That's already forgiven too
Yeah, it's it just means it frankly for a lot of them it means just
belief like agree really hard deep down in your heart. Right, but that's not repenting that's
believing that's a different thing. Right, those are different verbs. Yeah. I mean, right. So all
those calls to repent end up being kind of weirdly meaningless. Right in the New Testament. Because
Here's the thing as soon as I have this experience because I'm not a
Protestant and I talk to Protestants as soon as I start talking to you were
Process will protest you'll see see the YouTube comments below this video
over the next few days okay or even
what's the Protestant chat right now right now this is a straw man this is a
caricature right they're gonna they're gonna be saying all this we believe in
repents we believe you have to show contrition to be sorry for your sins we
believe you have to turn from sin we don't we believe
repentance means something right okay as soon as you say that to me in real time
I'm not gonna do anything.
comments with you. Sorry. Uh, see you today. That means I'm going to say to you, okay, so if someone
sins, someone sins, they believe they've they've come to faith at Christ, but they commit a sin and
they don't repent of it for whatever reason. Does that mean they're not forgiven?
They're going to tell me no. They're going to tell me no. So you can sit and talk all you want guys
about how you believe
leave repentance is necessary, right? And however you want to describe it, it's
feeling bad trying not to do it again. However, you want to describe it as it's
necessary. But when I push the word necessary to meaning you won't be forgiven,
meaning you're not saved anymore, because you sinned and didn't repent, you're
going to tell me, oh, no, no, no, no, no, no. Okay. So this is not a strong
manner of caricature. This is what your view boils down to. This is where your
if you go
goes if you push on it. And I know because I pushed on it. Yeah.
With plenty of Protestants. And that's where it always goes.
And always goes to, well, no, it isn't really necessary.
Yeah. And the reason when I come out and say it's not necessary for you,
you put straw man. Oh, right.
I mean, in the reason why is because they'll often say stuff like, well,
if that's necessary, if it's required, and that means you think you can add
something to your salvation. Like what you did was not the work.
Okay.
Yeah.
Yes. And in fact, that's the reality. If you're consistent and follow this through the way like Calvin
has to do because they're kind of ruthless about consistency. That's if you follow this through
like Calvin has to they'll tell you you trying to repent of your sins is not only a sin. Right?
Why would that be a sin? Because you're not trusting in Christ. Yeah. To pay the penalty for your
your sins, you're trying to do it yourself.
So if you make acts of repentance not only are those sins, but the consistent Calvinists will tell you that's an unforgivable sin.
Yeah, proof you are never. That's a sin that can't be forgiven. Why can't it be forgiven?
Because you're not trusting in Christ to have faith in the price for it.
I mean, it's one of these elements, you know, it's an element of traditional Calvinism, right?
right what they would call perseverance of the saints.
which in the kind of semi-Calvinist background that I had is described with the phrase
once saved, always saved, where basically your free will is operative up into the point
when you quote, get saved. And then after that, your free will can't do anything about that,
you know? Yeah. And when I say, when I talk about not repenting here,
okay, to head this off to, I'm not talking about quote-unquote life of unrepentance in.
I'm not saying you claim you are a Christian at some point, but...
You know, everybody sees you three days a week riding in a parade flute down the street
fornicating and offering incense to Zeus. That's not what I'm talking about.
Marty Grouse coming up here. Stuff happens. Anyway, okay. A parade. I'm just working down my head.
Okay, so, right, right. That's not I'm talking about just you don't repent. I'm talking about like
like, uh, you're a Christian, right?
And...
And you know what?
You have this bad habit of telling lies to get out of trouble.
And when confronted about it, you kind of feel bad about it, but you keep doing it and
you never really repent.
That's what I'm talking about.
None of you Protestants are going to tell me that you not repenting of that is going
to send you to hell.
I'm not saying it will.
But that that that that repents of that is necessary for salvation, right?
the kind of non-repetence I'm talking about.
about, right? Just own it. You don't believe repentance is required for salvation, right?
The problem is the new testament really makes it sound like it is. In fact, the new testament
really makes it sound like that's the main thing about it. About salvation is repentance,
not just once, but ongoing. As Martin Luther said, the first of the 95
DCs.
Lord said repent, he meant our whole life should be one of repentance.
Right.
Um, that, that's what the New Testament seems to say.
And so if your view comes to, well, repentance is it really necessary.
Right.
Uh, and especially if it comes to actually you trying to do acts of repentance
at reconciliation is a sin.
Now we've really turned things on our head.
Yeah. There is a point at which evangelical theology says that the one unforgivable sin
is trying to do good and please God. It's kind of weird, guys. And if you don't believe
it ever gets to that a couple months ago, the president of the United States said he was
trying to end wars because that was his best shot at getting into heaven. And a whole
bunch of prominent evangelicals took to the internet to say this proves he's not a
Christian. This is what proves he's not a Christian. That's
that he thinks you could do good things to please God and get
into heaven. Man, it was amazing. That out of all of the
behavior he's had in his life, that's the one that will send
you to hell, right? That should tell you you've arrived at an
absurd point. And you need to question we're kind of through
the looking glass here. What the Bible sort of I mean, you guys
all about the playing meeting of scripture.
That's kind of the opposite of the plain meeting of scripture, man. You got to admit, right?
Maybe something has gone wrong here.
So, uh, yeah, and
if you want let's look at a
particular very famous biblical text
and see if this text makes any sense with this idea of
of penal substitution, this transactional idea of
forgiveness. And that is 1 John 1 verse 9, which I mean all of us who grew up kind of Baptist.
We all memorized this verse a lot. 1 John 1, 9, if we confess our sins, he is faithful and just
to forgive us our sins and to cleanse us from all unrighteousness. Okay. So, the way that I was
This is Ray.
to interpret this verse, is that this verse is about becoming a Christian, going from
unbeliever to believer, but that's what it's about. But weirdly enough, it actually says
we, there at the beginning, and who has the easy talking to.
So you have to imagine that St. John is an unbeliever, right? You have to not read the first eight
verses of you.
pistol, which he is writing to a church of Christians who are his disciples, who are
his children in the Lord, and the we is he and them.
Yeah, the Christians.
That's what he's talking to.
So if this sentence is directed toward Christians, and you believe penal substitute
to share a tonin is true. What can it possibly mean?
Yeah, because it is a conditional statement.
Yeah, if then if if we confess our sins then then he is faithful to adjust to forgive us our sins and cleanse us from all on righteousness.
Yeah, and it's interesting to know that it's that the language there is cleanse which that's a tonement language.
That's purefication language. That's the language he uses throughout first Johnny talks about us being cleansed or purified by the blood of Christ.
It's not about, he's not using language.
of paying off or paying off or satisfied, warning off God's wrath.
None of that.
It's about us being cleansed by the blood of Christ, being purified and cleansed from sin.
But this isn't if then statement.
So, Christ took the penalty for all of them past, present and future.
What could it possibly mean that if you confess them, you will be forgiven them?
Yeah.
I mean, this isn't, this is, like, there's someone actually in the chat right now asking what...
does it mean to repent? This is one example of that. So confessing your sins is part of what repentance is.
You know, to repent, to repent quite simply is to live the way that God made us to live, to be faithful rather than to be unfaithful.
Yes. And to take actions that remediate the sin that you committed.
Yeah, it's not just I changed my mind, or I think differently than I used to. Yeah, you should think differently. He used to.
But like if you don't do anything, I'm
I mean, that's the kind of thing that's, you know,
seeing James calls faith without works, which is dead.
Yes.
And we all know this.
Okay, real world, real world.
This is the example I use.
I always use the example of adultery.
A man goes and commits adultery.
Right?
Cheats on his wife.
Okay.
Do you think if he comes home and says,
let's say he's an ex-Israelite.
Oh honey, I cheated on you, but don't worry.
I went and I offered a goat as a sacrifice,
so we're all good.
You
You think that's going to work?
Yeah.
Or modern day, he comes home, he says, well, you know, honey, I slept with another woman,
but I really prayed on it and Christ died for that sin too, and we're good.
I'm forgiven.
Yeah.
Does that work?
See really forgiven?
See really purified and cleansed from sin?
Right?
By the way,
I'll be fair. Let's say he's orthodox and he says, well, honey, I went to church and I confess that's into the priest and I've been forgiven. So we're good. That doesn't work that way either. Right. The orthodox church doesn't teach that that works that way. Right.
that person's repentance is the majority of it is him confessing that to his wife, what
he has done, and then doing the hard work over the course of years.
to try to rebuild that relationship and get her trust back.
Yeah.
And him being very accepting of the consequences,
being accepting of her distrust,
being accepting of her pain and anger,
and not pushing back or defending consultants.
Right.
All of that is his repentance.
And then at the end of that,
at the end of that journey,
When he's reconciled with his
wife, that is when he has really achieved an experience for
goodness. If you want a Bible example, right? People like
Bible examples, Zacchaeus. Christ goes to eat with Zacchaeus. He
could have walked in his door and said today's salvation has come
to this house because Christ is salvation, right? But that's not
when he says it. He comes to the eats with Zacchaeus and Zacchaeus
who is a tax collector stands up and says
Half of what I have I am going to give away to the poor and
Everything I have stolen I'm going to pay back five times
Right that second part being what's required of him from the Torah
Right he says he's going to do that and then when he says he is going to do that
That's when crisis to Zayn salvation has come to this house because he too is a child of Abraham
That's on crisis because
That is the key as repenting.
The repentance is those actions to make right
what he has done wrong in so far as it's in his power to do it.
And different things require different things to fix.
That's why there's different penalties for different sins
in the Torah.
There's different prescriptions to deal with different sins.
That's why you can fast different sins to a priest.
You receive different instructions and different guidance
in dealing with them.
right
because the goal is repentance, goal is justice, the goal is repairing the situation, healing
the situation. That's what forgiveness is. And repentance leads to forgiveness.
Yeah, you can't just say, well, we're technically it's been taken care of. Yeah. You know, yeah.
So I'm going to, you know, you're right. I'm going to go old school here, Father Andrew.
Oh, cuz I know it's almost better
I know.
I'm going to go old school.
I'm going to do something we haven't done for a long time on this show.
I'm going to call it Audible.
Uh-oh.
And a whole section of our material is going to go into another episode.
Oh, we haven't done this in a long time.
Yes, see?
Old school.
Well, you know, the reason we haven't done it a long time is because you've gotten better
about your scripting.
Maybe.
Or you've got better about keeping me on task in general.
That could be it as well.
You never know.
Yeah, so we have so many, but but I think this is a good I think we've got a through line for this episode
Absolutely, there's some other related things you're gonna talk about but we could build another episode around that
So you're not losing out on anything. No, you're not you're not you're just gonna have to be patient with this this material
So yeah, yeah, and I mean I think okay, so for
I think the place that I'm landing at the end of this episode is
number one
I think that a lot of the errors of trying to understand what's going on in the sacrificial system in the Old Testament and then how it's interpreted and applied and expanded on and transformed in the New Testament.
In many cases comes, frankly, from a lack of liturgical context. A lot of the people doing this interpretation do not have liturgical, well, I mean everyone has a liturgical thing that they're doing, but it's been so kind of.
kind of.
derasinated, you know. All of the liturgical tradition of Christianity, most of it maybe, has
been set aside, especially by evangelicals. Although it's interesting, it's interesting, some are now
kind of trying to recapture some of that. You know, that's something that we talk a lot about
on the Ayrionagus podcast is this sort of appropriation, this attempted appropriation
of liturgical elements, or other elements from Christian history.
I think that when you don't have a liturgical Christianity, then frankly, you have a lot of blindspots
in terms of reading the liturgics that is in the scriptures.
Right?
And so like, to me, the the locus classicus for that is, you know, putting sins on an animal
that is being sacrificed to God.
And as you have pointed out, that is nowhere in the scriptures.
Let's see.
never there, you have to read into it in one way or another. Like the only time that
sins are ever put on an animal explicitly is the goat for a zazel in the day of atonement
ritual, and that goat is not sacrificed. It is sent off into the wilderness. And you can't
say it's being sacrificed because if it is being sacrificed, and that means God is literally
telling the children of Israel to make a sacrifice to a demon that lives in the wilderness.
That is not what he's telling.
to do. So I think that there's a blind spot there and that's why the kind of liturgical
details like that are not as clear because the matrix within which to interpret and understand
liturgics is simply not present. To bring this home especially to the kind of Christianity
I was raised in and to make reference again to that video that I just went and looked
It has like 35 million views on YouTube or something like this.
And I-
And it's it's why though I know right right it's titled why I hate religion but love Jesus
This is based on number one. It's a complete misunderstanding of the word religion
Ridiculous misunderstanding the word religion
Um, but it's based on this idea that you know a lot of Christians will say I don't have a religion. I have a relationship
I don't have a religion. I have a relationship
You know, so I-
relationship is a good thing and religion is a bad thing. And religion is you know this ritualistic
dead religion you know or whatever whatever. And relationship is something else. Harvey wanted
to find how that works. But here's the thing is and I understand why that's being said. I understand
and I affirm the sincerity behind it. Like I know I know the people who say that why they say it
it, but the irony is.
When you have this transactional model of what sacrifices and salvation are about, then
isn't that what you're calling religion?
Like you're making a deal with God.
Whereas relationship is much more fulsome, has a lot more going on to it.
In a relationship, you can't just say, well look, I paid you off to your...
Now you need to forgive me.
Now a relationship means that there has to be change of life,
repentance, right?
Relationship, you know, the shared meal is an intimacy based on
everything being in the right order.
And of course, you know, like within a marriage,
marital intimacy is based on everything being in the right order.
You can't just say look I do.
did I did this x, y and z for you.
And so therefore our relationship is fine, which is literally what people who believe
in a transactional model of salvation.
That is literally what they believe.
Now whatever the x, y and z that has to be done for everything we find might vary from
one tradition to another, whatever it is you have to do to satisfy God, varies from one
tradition to another, but it is still a transactional approach.
That is religion, quote, unquote, not relationship.
So I mean that's...
the irony is this whole, I have a relationship, not a religion thing. It's by its own terms,
it's doing the opposite thing. But, but, here's why I want to end. People who do that,
most of them, even if in their, the theology that they speak, and like, you know, you
press them on it, Father Stephen, as you've mentioned, even if the theology that they speak
is still this kind of transaction.
a model and like, no, you can't do anything to contribute to your salvation. That would
actually be kind of a sin if you try to do these works of repentance in order to bring about
forgiveness, whatever. Even the people who might say that, they still know that they need to
live in repentance. They still do that. Only the most kind of anti-nomean weirdos don't.
Right?
They still have a sense you need to live your life right?
and there's something wrong with you if you don't.
And they still feel the existential brokenness and
mooning if they don't.
And they still try to put it back together if it gets broken.
Now, as they understand the repentance is necessary,
and there's still doing it, even if their theology,
in some cases, may say, you don't need to do that.
Why do you, one saved always saved?
What's wrong with you?
And so there's this kind of multiple personality disorder
going on.
Now, I believe that all faithfulness to God, even if it's done within a spiritual theological framework that is messed up, is faithfulness to God.
And God will judge to whatever extent, you know, he's going to save someone within that. That's for him to judge.
I'm not saying that that validates the theology. It doesn't.
But the truth is that there is an integrated way.
And that is what historic Christianity, Orthodox Christianity is.
You know, this sense of, well, I know I'm saved and I don't have to do anything more.
And the weird tension that exists between that and I need to get my life right, there
doesn't need to be attention.
And it doesn't mean contrary to the caricature that some have, so that they can have what
they call assurance.
It doesn't mean you live in this constant anxiety
and my state of grace out of state of grace.
My experience is in North of Execration
for almost 30 years does not include that idea.
Because
the way of
demination is not
whoops, I sinned or
like truly accidentally or even like I had a fall
No, no, no.
know the way of demination is the center with the high hand. The center who says, you
know what? I know I'm sitting and I'm gonna keep sitting. Not just, oh man, I keep
sitting. God helped me not to sin again today. That's repentance. Even if you
fall every single day, you get up every single day. That's repentance. It's the
center who says, I don't care. This is the way that I'm going to live. I'm not
not going to change. I'm not even going to try to change. That's the center.
with a high hand. That's the center who's in really deep trouble. Not the person who
keeps sitting. It's the person who decides not to repent. And so if you're living a life
where you've decided to repent and you're doing it, even if you keep sitting, then you
are being faithful. You are fulfilling the commandments of God. And that is a place of assurance.
so much better
of assurance then, well, I know everything's fine. I don't have to bother now because, you know,
that's predicated upon, it's predicated usually upon the idea of that you know that you were sincere
at some particular moment. And you don't really know if you were really, really sincere, that I
really mean it. I knew a lot of people that when got baptized multiple times or kept quote-unquote
re-dedicating the lives of Christ because it couldn't be sure that they were really sincere at that moment.
moment. No, maybe I'll do it this time. But it's actually much easier to answer the question,
am I continuing to repent? It's not a psychological game. It's, did I get up and start again? Okay, I did.
My father-converser told me I did. I'm doing it. That's a sure it's. That's a sure it's. That's
peace. That's real peace. And that's a peace that actually connects with the 3D life of the
the Christian on the ground.
So that's my those are my big takeaways from this conversation today
So I'm gonna take that baton and I'm gonna push it way farther
So that there are people
This is just folks in the evangelical world there are folks in the orthodox church who are
Shall we say
Overly assured.
There's salvation. Don't take the idea that they need to live a Christian life seriously, right?
That's the thing that happens. Unlike evangelicalism and ideas like what saved all I saved, they don't
actually have the theology to back that up, which kind of makes it even weirder. But
guess what, those folks aren't going to listen to this three hour plus podcast. So those are
those are the kind of folks we're mostly talking to.
And what's really inspiring this for me is not so much what Father Andrew said though I'm taking off from that.
But some questions I've been getting lately when I do Q&As online and stuff.
And I feel free to pick on and make fun of people, but these are people I'm not picking on or making fun of.
These are people who, you know, what I have left of a heart goes out to.
You know, like I got a question from somebody, how much detail do I have to...
given my confession of a sin in order to be forgiven.
And I've had people constantly
when you're a priest and you hear confessions.
Is this a sin?
I'm not sure if this is a sin.
Is this something I need to confess?
Right?
And in terms of what Father Andrew was just talking about,
There's a lot of, especially on the internet, when you see evangelicals and orthodox Christians
getting into it, right?
There's all of this pushback against because so often what the evangelical tries to use
as a trump card against the orthodox Christian is assurance of salvation, claiming they have
it and we don't, right?
And the kind of smug way that's put
online, right? Which isn't the reality I understand of actual evangelical Christians,
but that smugway it's put online then gets this pushback from Orthodox circles of like no
you can't be assured of your salvation, right? And I worry about how the folks who are
asking me those kind of questions hear that. Here Orthodox people in public space is again
again saying you can
can't be assured of your salvation.
Right, over and over again.
And so, this isn't even like the idea of scrupulosity,
like that you find in Roman Catholicism, where people are overlooking Sir Rutheron Sins,
because it's not from a neurotic level.
It's from like a pain level, it's from a level of fear.
Right.
that in the end when they stand before the judgment seat of Christ, right,
that they're they're going to be condemned and no person should have that.
No person should have that
that kind of fear
that leads to despair
of other Christian life.
No one should be super worried about that.
I see a lot of it. I've had to... Here's another example. On a practical level,
I've had to put a moratorium on confessions right after POSCA.
I've had people who I received into the church like baptized for the remission of their
sins on Holy Saturday, want to come Wednesday of bright week to confession.
like we can't take a while to celebrate.
Christ victory over sin and death and hate is the fact that those are sins have been blotted out by his blood. We can't we can't even celebrate that a week or two before
We're back to being concerned that we're going to go to hell for the horrible thing we've done.
Right that that's not normal. That's not really repentance.
Right?
Real repentance and assurance. All this is found in...
Knowing God. Right? Christ said that's life. Life is to know God and Jesus Christ to me is sent.
That's what Christ says. That's life.
God wants you. Whenever you are listening to this, God wants you
to have eternal life.
That's what God wants. That's what He desires. And that's not what He wants and desires in a passive way.
Okay, I can prove that. Christ lived, suffered, died a horrific death
so that you could have eternal life. Okay, He didn't do that
So that you could arrive on the
day of judgment and oh he got close. He didn't do that so he could nitpick your life on that
day and find some reason to exclude you. Quite the opposite. Because it's not just what
Christ did. It's what the Holy Spirit has been doing in your life, your whole life.
You as a person, your whole life.
life from conception. What God, the Holy Spirit, has been doing in your life
continuously to try to bring you to salvation. That's why that's how I know
because all of that is real. That's what God's goal is. God's goal. On the day of
judgment, there can be lots of different types of people, but one type of person
there will not
not a single one is a person who loved God with all his heart. Did everything he
could to follow Jesus Christ as best he understood and is condemned.
That person will not exist on the day of judgment and that means it can't be you.
Okay. So the assurance comes in knowing that God loves you.
Everyone, even Esau, sorry Calvinist, right?
He loves you.
He wants you to have eternal life.
He has literally moved heaven and earth for that to happen.
All you have to do is not say no.
Yes, I know.
know, over the course of your life you've said no a whole bunch of times. Me too. Little
ways and big ways you've said no. To what he wanted to do. To your salvation. But here's
the thing. You're still alive and listening to me now. So you have another chance to say
Yes.
Your know is not final.
None of them are.
and he doesn't want them to be. God is not trying to sift people out to send them to hell.
He's trying to bring people to salvation. So don't worry about the transactions. When you
come to Confessions, make your best confession. Do the best you can on that day. It's never
going to be perfect. Not once, are you going to have a perfect
not once are you going to have a perfect act of contrition, not once are you going to
remember all your sins, not once are you going to really be fully 100% honest with your spiritual
father? I know. I'm not either. Okay. God isn't looking at that as a reason to exclude you.
He's looking at that as a step in the right direction.
Let's take the next one and the next one and the next one and the next one.
Because the road is all leading in one direction.
That's what I have to say to that.
Amen.
Well, that's our show for tonight.
Thank you for tuning in everyone.
If you didn't happen to get through to us live, you can still get in touch.
You can email us at Lordofspirits.nationafate.com.
You can message us at our Facebook page where you can leave us a voicemail.
At SpeakPipe.com slash Lordofspirits.
If you have basic questions about orthodox Christianity or you need help.
finding a parish in the 3D world, go to orthodoxintro.org.
Join us for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 6 p.m. Eastern
3 p.m. Pacific. You see my problem is this, I'm dreaming away, wishing that heroes they truly
exist. And if you are on Facebook, you can follow our page, you can join our big old discussion
group, leave ratings and reviews, and share this show with a friend of yours. And finally,
be sure to go to www.engstrafet.com.strowksupport and help.
make sure we in lots of other AFR podcasts
or stay on the air.
I cry watching the days.
Can't you see I'm a fool in so many ways?
Thank you.
Good night.
And may God bless you all.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father
Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung, a listener-supported presentation of ancient
faith radio.
I be held and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts and
the elders, and the number of them was ten thousand times ten thousand than thousands
of thousands, saying with a loud voice worthy as the land that was slain to receive power
and riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.